In the year 1815, the English colonial
official Thomas Stamford Raffles would
travel across the island of
Java in what is today Indonesia.
At this time, the world was torn by war.
In Europe, the Napoleonic Wars were raging,
and the Earth's oceans had become just another
battlefront. The lush tropical island of Java
had been until recently a Dutch colony, but the
Netherlands had been conquered by Napoleon in
his advance across Europe, and so, the Dutch
colonies had fallen under the control of the
French. Now the British desired to take Java
for themselves and strike a blow at Napoleon's
overseas empire. In 1811, British Marines
launched an invasion of Java, landing among
its coral reefs and sky-blue oceans, clambering
through its shady mangrove forests, and up its
beaches of black volcanic sand, climbing the steep
cliffs in the shadow of its towering volcanoes.
From there they overwhelmed the inexperienced
Dutch defenders, and took the island for the
British Empire. With them came the Englishman
Thomas Stamford Raffles, who later wrote about
these events. Holland had ceased to be an
independent nation, and in the year 1811,
the French flag was hoisted over Java. But
on the 17th of September of the same year,
a capitulation was entered into, by which all the
dependencies fell into the hands of Great Britain.
Raffles was a lifelong sailor, and had actually
been born at sea on a ship commanded by his father
off the coast of Jamaica. He became a clerk in the
British East India Company at the age of fourteen,
and from there became a true company
man. He had spent the best part of the
last decade furthering the interests
of British colonialism in East Asia,
and had even become fluent in the language of
Malay. When Java was captured by the British,
partly as a result of his skill at
languages, Raffles was granted the
position of Lieutenant Governor. At the
age of just thirty, Raffles found himself
in charge of an island a thousand kilometers
across, home to more than six million people.
Raffles was fascinated by Java. He
remarked on its dramatic landscape of
soaring volcanoes and steamy rainforests, its
fertile rice terraces and remarkable culture,
as he wrote home to King George III. The
gracious permission which I have received
affords me an opportunity of interesting your
royal highness in favor of the amiable and
ingenious people whose country they describe. A
chain of very high mountains runs along the whole
length of Java. Even in July and August, the
atmosphere is refreshed by occasional showers,
and the landscape is at all times of the
year covered with the brightest green.
But most of all, he was fascinated by Java's
antiquities. Everywhere among its forests
and shaded rice terraces could be seen the
remains of the countless temples, palaces,
and even whole ancient cities left in ruins.
A few years later, around 1815, he embarked on
a journey around the island, with the aim of
surveying these ruins and writing a book. Although
by then Java was an overwhelmingly Muslim land,
Raffles found everywhere the remains of an
older culture hiding just beneath the surface,
as he writes in his work, The History of Java. The
Muhammadan religion, as it present exists on Java,
seems only to have penetrated the surface,
and to have taken but little root in the
heart of Javans. But the antiquities
of Java consist of ruins of edifices,
and in particular of temples sacred to the
former worship; images of deities found within
them and scattered throughout the country,
either sculpted in stone or cast in metal,
inscriptions on stone and copper in
ancient characters and ancient coins.
Raffles was fascinated by these remains,
which seemed to confirm stories he had heard,
stories of a great empire that had risen up
on that island, a thriving combination of
Hinduism and Buddhism that had flourished for
centuries, spread its influence across the sea
to countless other islands in the Indonesian
archipelago, and built what may have been
one of the largest empires in Southeast
Asia. This was the empire of Majapahit.
The numerous and interesting remains of former
art and grandeur, which exist in the ruins
of temples and other edifices the abundant
treasures of sculpture and statuary either
lay entirely buried under rubbish or were
but partially examined. Nothing, therefore,
of the ancient history of the people, of their
institutions prior to the introduction of
Muhammadanism, of their magnificence and power,
could be accurately known or fully relied on. The
grandeur of their ancestors sounds like a fable,
and it is only when it can be traced in monuments,
which cannot be falsified, that we are led to
give credit to their traditions concerning it.
Raffles became convinced that he could find the
remnants of the civilization of Majapahit, and so,
he traveled the length and breadth of the island
and visited every ruined site he could along the
way. He stopped at the ancient cities of Kediri
and Singhasari, and found there the crumbling
remains of city walls, palaces, and carved
statues of the Buddha alongside Hindu gods.
But when he got to the valley of the Brantas
River in East Java, the locals advised him not to
go near the ruins. They told him that a terrible
curse still lingered over those crumbling stones.
The natives have a superstition that the
site of this ancient capital cannot be
visited without some misfortune attaching to the
party who undertake the visit. Those whom I had,
with some difficulty, induced
to accompany me to the spot,
did not fail to assure me that I should
lose my government within the year. Finally,
Raffles visited the great capital of
Majapahit, which his guides told him
lay buried near the town of Trowulan. At Trowulan,
Raffles hoped to find a magnificent ruined city,
testifying to the former greatness of this power.
But when he arrived, he would be disappointed.
He would find little more than a scatter
of broken brickwork and assorted sculpture
littering the landscape, buried in volcanic
ash, and shaded beneath the towering teak trees.
A village adjacent is called Tra Wulan, or the
Light of the Moon. The ruins of the palace and
several gateways of burnt brick are to be
seen, but the whole country for many miles
is thickly covered with a stately teak forest,
which appears to have been the growth of ages,
so that it is difficult to trace the outline
of this former capital. Ruins of temples,
mostly executed in brick, are scattered about the
country for many miles, and attest to the extent
and grandeur of this pride of Java. The temples
are beautifully decorated with representations
of flowers and other peculiar ornaments,
which it would be difficult to describe.
In fact, the local people turned out to
be right, and perhaps Raffles should have
listened to their warnings. Raffles would only
govern the island of Java for another year.
The Napoleonic Wars soon came to an end, and
the British returned the colony to the now
independent Dutch, relieving Raffles
of his post, and he would go on to
suffer more misfortune in the years that
followed. Just ten years later, he would
have a stroke likely caused by an underlying
condition in the blood vessels of his brain.
This stroke would kill him the day before his 45th
birthday. As Raffles wandered about those ruins of
crumbling red brick at the site of the ancient
city of Majapahit, he had no idea that his fate
was already sealed by the birth defect lurking in
his head. But perhaps that day he thought about
life and death as he walked beneath the shade of
that teak forest and listened to the calling of
koels and myna birds high in the trees. Perhaps
he thought about the rise and fall of empires and
the changing fortunes of the world. Perhaps
he wondered how such a power had risen up on
the island of Java and left such a mark on the
memories and imaginations of that land's people.
Perhaps he asked himself how its people had
constructed these temples and palaces, these walls
and reservoirs, carved such beautiful and haunting
monuments, and then fallen all at once into ruin.
My name's Paul Cooper, and you're listening to
the Fall of Civilizations podcast. Each episode,
I look at a civilization of the past that rose
to glory and then collapsed into the ashes of
history. I want to ask; what did they have in
common? What led to their fall? And what did
it feel like to be a person alive at the time who
witnessed the end of their world? In this episode,
I want to tell the story of the Majapahit Empire
of medieval Indonesia. I want to show how this
empire of the islands grew up on the volcanic land
of Java, and how it beat the odds to survive in
a world of medieval superpowers. I want to show
how Majapahit expanded its influence and dominion
to other lands over the seas, and undertook
voyages that have few precedents in history,
and I want to show what happened to bring this
empire of the islands finally crashing down.
The surface of planet Earth
is a thin crust of solid rock,
which sits over the softer and
much hotter mantle beneath it.
This crust can be as much as 80 kilometers thick
in places, and as thin as 10 kilometers in others,
and it is divided into seven major tectonic
plates. The largest of these is the Pacific Plate.
It is a vast sheet of solid rock more than 100
million square kilometers in size that makes
up much of the floor of the Pacific Ocean,
and which alone accounts for about a fifth
of Earth's total surface. The Pacific Plate is
made up almost entirely of oceanic crust, which
is different to the continental crust that we all
live on. Oceanic crust is typically much thinner,
but made of denser basalt rock. For this reason,
whenever it impacts with other tectonic plates,
the Pacific Plate is pushed downwards into
the Earth's upper mantle, creating a zone
of subduction, and these subduction zones are
renowned for their violent volcanic activity.
Due to its immense size and density, the
Pacific Plate has the most subduction zones of
any tectonic plate, and as a result, its borders
are the most volcanically active areas on Earth.
This ring of raging volcanoes stretches in a vast
horseshoe shape for more than 40,000 kilometers,
or about the circumference of the Earth, from
the southern tip of South America all around
the Western shore of the Americas,
and then through the sea down the
Eastern coast of Asia. To geologists
it is called the Circum-Pacific Belt,
but in popular usage, it has come to be known
by another name: the Pacific Ring of Fire.
The 19th-century English geologist
George P. Scrope was one of the
first to describe this far-ranging phenomenon.
A striking and constant delineation of
volcanic spiracles is displayed in the
numerous archipelagos which border
the Eastern coast of Asia. Beginning
from the peninsula of Kamchatka,
Japan, the Loo-choo, Philippines,
and Moluccas form a scarcely interrupted linear
series of volcanic islands, amongst which many
contain vents in habitual activity, and bearing
marks of recent and extremely violent eruptions.
The Pacific Ring of Fire is home to
three-quarters of all the world's volcanoes,
and 90% of the earthquakes on Earth take place
along this line. The Ring of Fire has given us
some of the world's most iconic peaks, including
the elegant cone of Mount Fuji in Japan, and the
violently explosive Mount St. Helens in the United
States, as well as the volcanoes of Mount Tambora
and Krakatoa, whose 1815 and 1883 eruptions
were among the largest in recorded history.
As it is dragged down into the depths
of the planet, the subducting Pacific
Plate has also created some of the lowest
places on the Earth's surface, giving rise
to a series of dramatic oceanic trenches. The
deepest of these, known as the Mariana Trench,
reaches a sea depth of 11 kilometers, deeper than
Mount Everest is tall, and in the areas where the
Ring of Fire passes through open ocean, it has
also created a huge number of volcanic islands.
As volcanoes erupt under the sea,
magma spews out of the planet's
mantle and cools on contact with cold
sea water into solid rock. Over time,
whole islands form around these volcanoes,
and on these islands, the lives and deaths
and dramas and tragedies of millions of human
lives have played out throughout history.
Perhaps the region where the Pacific
Ring of Fire has had the most effect
in sculpting the landscape is in the area
of what is today Malaysia and Indonesia.
Here the Ring of Fire has lifted thousands
of islands large and small from the sea,
and this archipelago has come to
be known by a name that in old
Javanese meant simply the outer
lands . This name is Nusantara.
The archipelago today called Nusantara lies
across an area of ocean wider than the continental
United States, and laid over a map of Europe would
stretch from France as far east as Northern India.
The archipelago is today home to more than 700
languages, six major religions, and more than 300
ethnicities, and since modern humans first arrived
on these islands, they have given rise to a huge
variety of different peoples. One Chinese Buddhist
monk named Faxian, who sailed to India in the 4th
century in search of rare religious manuscripts,
describes the perils and beauties of this ocean.
In this sea there are many pirates. The sea
is boundless in extent. It is impossible to
know east or west, and one can only advance by
observing the sun, moon, or stars. If it is dark,
rainy weather, you have to follow the wind in
perfect uncertainty. During the darkness of night,
one only sees the great waves striking
each other and shining like fire,
whilst shoals of sea monsters of
every description surround the ship.
Today, the complex geography of this region
can prove confusing to many. As you listen,
if you find yourself getting lost in the different
names of islands and seas referenced in this
episode, it's worth remembering that you're
not alone. This is by far the densest region
for islands anywhere in the world, and in fact,
the government of Indonesia itself has struggled
to come up with a definitive answer to exactly
how many islands there are within its borders.
One 2002 study using the satellite images
Landsat identified more than 18,000 islands,
while another 2010 study gave a lower figure,
noting that only around 9,000 even have names.
Nearly 90% of Indonesia's islands are tiny,
coming in at less than a kilometer squared.
Other islands are massive. The archipelago
contains the world's second-largest island of
Papua or New Guinea, the third-largest of Borneo,
and the sixth-largest of Sumatra. In land area,
each of these is larger than Japan or the size
of the United Kingdom and France combined. But
while this archipelago is home to some enormous
islands, these tend to be rocky and mountainous,
their interiors covered in impenetrable
rainforest, and generally sparsely populated.
It is the fifth-largest island in the archipelago
that has had perhaps the greatest impact of all,
and this is the place where our story
begins, the long, narrow island of Java.
Java is a volcanic island shaped like a
cigar running just south of and roughly
parallel to the equator. It's little
over 100 kilometers wide north to south,
but stretches for more than a
thousand kilometers east to west,
and the center of the island is dominated
by a rocky spine of conical volcanoes.
A medieval Javanese creation myth called
the Tantu Panggelaran describes how the
island was once floating free in the ocean
before the gods decided to nail it down.
The island of Java was unsteady, constantly
moving up and down, as it had no great mountains,
not to mention human beings. For this reason,
Lord Jagat-Pramana arose and promptly performed
yoga on the island of Java. The deity
stood facing east. He churned the water,
and it turned into foam and turned
into mountains. For this reason,
we have what is called the land above the clouds
now. Now the gods Brahma and Vishnu agreed,
and made human beings. They kneaded lumps of clay
and formed them into humans of perfect beauty.
Today, partly as a result of its rich volcanic
soil and its heavy rainfall and strong sun,
Java is the world's most populous island. It is
home to more than 150 million people, despite its
land area being only about the size of England,
making it one of the most densely populated places
on Earth. More people live on Java than in the
whole of Russia, despite it being about 130 times
smaller, and its capital of Jakarta recently took
the top spot as the world's most populated city.
This reputation for abundance
goes back to ancient times.
The Hindu epic poem the Ramayana,
written around two thousand years ago,
already mentions Java as a place of wealth. The
island of Yava is decorated with seven kingdoms,
gold and silver islands rich in gold mines, and a
cold mountain that touches the sky with its peak.
Even in ancient times, the island had a
global reputation. It was prominent enough
in the 2nd century that the Greek writer and
geographer Claudius Ptolemy included it in his
work Geographia, right at the farthest edge of the
known world. He describes an island named Yabadiu,
a name which he says means the island of barley
, possibly referring to the hardy grain millet,
which has been an important foodstuff there
for centuries before the introduction of rice.
As a result of its inclusion in Ptolemy's work,
the island would also appear in a number
of medieval and early modern mappa mundi,
or maps of the world, although few Europeans
could agree on where exactly the island was.
In these maps, it usually appears somewhere
wedged between Africa and Asia, and always as
far away as it was possible to get. But for
the people who lived on the island of Java,
it was the very center of the world. According to
Javanese legend, it was where the gods had first
created humanity and taught them the secrets of
civilization, as the Tantu Panggelaran recounts.
Such were the instructions of Lord Guru to all
the gods; they descended to Java. The God Brahma
became a blacksmith. The Earth served as his
anvil, water as his tongs, light as his fire, and
wind as his bellows, and the sky as his hammer.
Lord Wiswakarma descended as a carpenter and made
a house, and people followed him and made houses.
The Lord Ishwara descended and taught beneficial
words, in particular about the ten kinds of
good conduct and the five fields of learning.
Since it sits virtually on the equator, Java
experiences very little variation in sunlight
throughout the year. In fact, its shortest day
is only 48 minutes shorter than its longest.
The western side of the island also enjoys very
dependable monsoon rains from the Indian Ocean,
which combine with the extremely fertile volcanic
soil so that farmers could grow all year round,
and could often harvest three whole crops of
rice each year. The 14th-century Chinese source,
the Song Shi or History of the Sung Dynasty,
describes the great abundance of this island.
The country is flat and fit for agriculture.
Its products are rice, hemp, and peas,
there being no wheat. Salt is obtained by boiling
sea water, and there is an abundance of fish,
turtles, poultry, ducks, goats, and cattle,
which they kill for the purpose of eating.
Their fruit are papaya, coconuts,
plantains, sugarcane, and taro.
From about the fifth century on,
this vast agricultural potential
would give birth to thriving societies, and
these would go on to construct elaborate,
monumental architecture. For nearly the
next thousand years, most of these societies
would arise in the west of Java. One king of
this time named Purna-varman left one of the
earliest stone inscriptions carved into a large
boulder in the Ciaruteun River. The powerful,
illustrious, and brave king, the famous
Purna-varman of the Taruma-nagara kingdom,
whose print of the foot soles are
the same as those of God Vishnu.
The inscription is accompanied by a
carved imprint of both of the king's feet,
symbolically stamping his
ownership on the territory.
By the sixth or seventh century, a power known
as Kaling seems to have risen up in Central Java,
and a description of it was included in the
Chinese source known as the Xin Tangshu,
or the New History of the Tang Dynasty.
Kaling is also called Java. It is situated in the
southern ocean. The people make fortifications of
wood, and even the largest houses are covered with
palm leaves. They have couches of ivory and mats
of the outer skin of bamboo. The land produces
tortoiseshell, gold and silver, rhinoceros horns,
and ivory. The country is very rich. They have
letters and are acquainted with astronomy.
These early kingdoms seem to have met
with great success on the island of Java,
but little has survived of
their records, their literature,
or their architecture. But all that would change
with the founding of a kingdom known as Mataram.
The name Mataram comes from the Sanskrit
word matr , meaning mother , and likely
meant something like motherland .
This kingdom grew up not in the west,
but in the highlands of Central Java, right in the
shadow of the great volcanoes Merbabu and Merapi.
The people of Mataram were the first to truly
take advantage of this mountainous landscape,
and cultivated the steep slopes of
this area using concentric terraces
of rice fields fed and drained by intricate
systems of canals and stone-lined channels.
This kingdom of the mountains was originally
Hindu, and worshipped primarily the god Shiva,
the god of creation and destruction.
Living as they did on a land constantly torn
apart and remade by the destructive power of
the volcanoes, it's no mystery why this god
would have held sway in the kingdom of Mataram.
But with the rise of a dynasty known
as the Shailendras in the 8th century,
Mataram began to drift further
towards a new religion, Buddhism.
In this period, Mataram would become what's known
to historians as an Indianized Hindu-Buddhist
kingdom, with elements of both religions combined
into a syncretic whole. These religions became so
intertwined over the centuries that followed that
the epic Tantu Panggelaran even recounts the story
of one god who came down to earth and divided
himself into two holy sages, one Buddhist and one
Hindu, so that he could spread both religions at
the same time. Let us tell about Mahampu Palyat.
He returned to the island of Java. He divided
his body into two, and it became a Shivaite and a
Buddhist. Off they went and arrived in Java. They
headed for Girah, and set up a monastery together.
The kings of Java would even come to
be known by the title Batara Siwa Buda,
meaning the divine lord Shiva Buddha , a royal
figure in whom the two sacred beings were fused.
This was in general a period
of coexistence and unity,
and it's in this era that some of Java's
most remarkable monuments would be built.
The kings of the mountain kingdom of Mataram
were ambitious builders. Around the year 850,
they completed construction of a great temple
to Shiva, the towering Prambanan temple, which
still sends its eight sturdy spires up into the
skies of southern Java. It is the second-largest
Hindu structure in Southeast Asia, behind only
Angkor Wat in Cambodia, and it left its mark not
just on the landscape but in the name of the
year in which its construction was completed.
By this time, the Javanese had adopted
a unique system of naming each year,
giving them what are known as moon chronograms,
or in Javanese, chandra-sengkala. This system used
the Indian Shaka calendar, which assigned numbers
to the years the way we do today, like 1066, 1939,
or 2026. But the Javanese developed this Indian
calendar with their own poetic flourish. They
gave each number from 0 to 10 an array of
possible symbols like the sun, moon, fire,
and other elements which they could choose from to
give the year a name that seemed the most fitting.
For example, the 18th-century Balinese chronicle
named the Babadgumi gives one year the name Gajah
Api Anin Watu, or Elephant, Fire, Wind, Stone, due
to a particularly violent eruption of the volcano
Mount Agung that took place in East Bali. Another
year in which a fierce battle took place was named
Paksa Sikara Bah Bumi, or the Force of Violence
Moving Upon the Earth. Due to this system,
we can sometimes get a sense from the names
that years were given of the overriding mood
in the kingdom; sometimes a mood of joy and
celebration, at others of despair and sorrow.
On the year that the kings of Mataram completed
the Prambanan temple, they were clearly proud
of their achievement, and because of its eight
towering main shrines, they named the year in
honor of it. In our calendar it was 856,
but in the Shaka calendar it was called
Eight Mountains of the Holy Monks, as recorded
in a text known as the Shavghra Inscription.
In the time of the Shaka year Eight Mountains of
the Holy Monks, the statue of the god was finished
and inaugurated. After the Shiva sanctuary
had been completed in its divine splendor,
the course of the river was changed
so that it rippled along the grounds.
Then the grounds were inaugurated
as temple grounds with the gods.
Other temples built by the kings of Mataram, such
as the sprawling temple at Sewu, are thought to
have been Buddhist since they were built in
the form of a mandala, an important geometrical
concept in Buddhism that is used to conceptualize
the shape of the universe. But chief among their
works is the structure that would become what is
still the largest Buddhist temple in the world.
It's thought that the Javanese of the
time called it Bhumi Shambhara Bhudhara,
or the Mountain of Combined Virtues
of the Ten Stages of Buddha-hood.
But today it is known by a name meaning
only the Great Buddha or Borobudur.
Borobudur rises like a mountain from
the river plains right in the shadow
of the great volcano Mount Merapi. This vast
complex consists of nine stacked platforms
rising like a wedding cake up to a height of
35 meters, and topped by a central dome. One
heritage worker, Gerard Bolla, describes
the appearance of this incredible temple.
Borobudur, the mountain of the
virtues, is first of all a landscape,
the landscape which over a thousand years ago
met the eyes of those who came on pilgrimage
here to seek inner peace. It has hardly changed.
In the distance, two volcanoes, one ever menacing,
glows red in the night. All around in the middle
distance, a ring of mountains. Built on this
same volcanic stone, Borobudur emerges from a
delicate green background of tropical vegetation.
The design of Borobudur, like the temple
at Sewu, is an enormous mandala visible
from above. But this mandala covers the area of
two football pitches, and guides its pilgrims
up through a series of concentric walkways and
stairways carved out of black volcanic stone.
These are all lined with nearly 3,000 carved
friezes and five hundred Buddha statues created by
the finest craftsmen the kingdom could find. The
archaeologist Professor Raden Soekmono, who was in
charge of the project to restore the great temple
in modern times, describes its spiritual function.
For the ardent Buddhist, it is the highest wisdom
that leads to the ultimate salvation, and for the
technician, the highest degree of expertise that
leads to the appropriate fulfillment of his duty.
In both cases, Borobudur is the embodiment of
such a deeply felt wish. It is a prayer in stone.
The symbolism of this structure, shaped like
a mountain, would likely have been obvious
to the early medieval Javanese. The gods had once
placed the mountains of Java to secure the island
in place and bring stability to the land. Now
their king did the same thing, placing his own
mountain on the landscape to act as a testament to
the lasting stability of his reign, and Borobudur
was built to last. It was constructed entirely
without mortar or cement, carving its two million
blocks of volcanic stone into intricate
interlocking shapes to hold them together.
This design has meant that it has largely
survived the countless earthquakes that have
taken place over the last millennium in one
of the world's most seismically active zones.
As well as the shifting ground beneath their
feet, the builders also had the heavy rainfall
of the Javanese monsoon to contend with. For this
reason, they equipped the site of Borobudur with
more than a hundred spouts for drainage, each
carved in the shape of a giant or sea dragon,
so that when it rained, water would have poured
from their mouths. But the most remarkable and
haunting feature of this monument is the thousands
of reliefs carved all around its galleries.
Many of these carvings show stories from
the lives of the Buddha ascending through
kilometers of galleries, and in this way, the
monument is a story brought to life in stone.
But alongside this religious narrative, others
show scenes of simple daily life for all the
different levels of Javanese society. In these
carvings, we see people carrying woven baskets
for winnowing and steaming rice, and stirring
milk rice in pots. We see people working in the
fields and shopping in a bustling urban
marketplace, people carrying baskets of
tropical fruit and nets full of fish, all of
their faces looking out from the stone, frozen
in a moment that passed by more than a thousand
years ago. The Chinese History of Liang describes
the dress and appearance of the people of Java,
which can be seen in the reliefs of Borobudur.
Men and women have the upper part of the
body naked. Their hair hangs loosely down,
and around their lower limbs they only
use a sarong of cotton. The king and the
nobles have a thin, flowered cloth for
covering the upper part of their body.
They wear a girdle of gold and golden
rings in their ears. Young girls cover
themselves with a cloth of cotton
and wear an embroidered girdle.
In these carvings, we also get a sense for courtly
life. We see the king coming and going on his
elephant, his courtiers, and the palace women.
In some carvings, we see the king and his nobles
enjoying a splendid feast known as a Mahamangsa.
One 12th-century Javanese epic poem known as
the Bhomantaka, or Death of Bhoma, describes
the sumptuous sight of one of these feasts.
The dishes were salted eggs, the pork neck cuts,
ayung-ayung, and pabekan, vegetables in hot sauce,
lichin and chekah, red mince of tripe with its
various red salads, and sizzling dripping of
turtle, and the boiled vegetables, langsuban
with marrow and tongue in rolls, mushrooms
steamed in leaves, crisp flakes of jellyfish,
liver with rump accompanied by roasted lungs,
breast bone, intestines on skewers with fat and
hot kebabs. The banana heart was sweet, and there
was no lack of prawns, crabs, salted fish, and
muscles. Pickled meats, grilled meats, wuku and
various skewered meats, doves, pupuk birds, and
wild pigeon made them clutch in all directions.
Some of these 9th-century carvings even depict
recipes that are still enjoyed in Indonesia today,
among them a dish called tumpeng, a tall
cone of rice surrounded by side dishes,
which is still prepared for special occasions.
But one particular feature of these
carvings has always captured the
imagination of those who visit the ruins.
These are the so-called Borobudur ships.
In among the scenes of daily life are carved
the shapes of five large seagoing vessels,
graceful and high-sided, which show just
how accomplished the Javanese had become
as shipbuilders and sailors. And so, it's no
surprise that it was around this time that the
people of Java began to gain a reputation
around the world as traders and pirates.
The Javanese of the Mataram period sailed in
large ships that were often built from teak.
This kind of wood was prized for its strength and
its high oil content, which gives it a natural
water resistance even without varnishing, and
gives it a distinct rich aroma like fine leather.
These ships were built without nails, using only
interlocking joints and wooden dowels, and with
ingenious arrangements of sails. The 3rd-century
Chinese writer Wan Chen, in his work Nanzhou Yiwu
Zhi, or Strange Things of the Southern Lands,
describes the sight of these majestic vessels.
The people sometimes rig as many as four sails,
which they carry in a row from bow to stern.
The four sails do not face directly forward, but
are set obliquely, and so arranged that they can
all be fixed in the same direction to receive
the wind and to spill it. If it is violent,
the sailors diminish or augment the surface
of the sails according to the conditions.
Thus, these ships sail without avoiding
strong winds and dashing waves,
by the aid of which they can make great speed.
To Wan Chen and other Chinese writers, these
Javanese ships were so remarkable because China
itself would not develop large oceangoing vessels
until around the 9th century, or 600 years later.
In fact, the Chinese held the ships of these
islanders in such reverence that no foreign
craft were permitted to sail within range
of the main port of Guangdong or Canton,
as the 16th-century Portuguese
diplomat Tom Pires recounts.
They say that the Chinese made this law
about not being able to go to Canton for
fear of the Javanese and Malays, for it is
certain that one of these people's ships
would rout twenty Chinese ships. Such
is their fear of Malays and Javanese.
This fear appears to have been warranted. The
inscriptions of the Cham people of Vietnam and
the Khmer in Cambodia frequently reference
the arrival of fearsome seagoing raiders,
who are thought to have sailed
from islands like Sumatra and Java.
One inscription in the Po Nagar temple in
Vietnam describes one such raid in the year 774.
Ferocious, pitiless, dark-skinned men
born in other countries, whose food
was more horrible than corpses,
and who were vicious and furious,
came in ships, took away the temple
statue, and set fire to the temple.
The Javanese were in part able to become
such successful sailors due to the extremely
predictable wind patterns that take place in this
part of the world. During the rainy season from
December to March, the winds blow in over Java
from the Asian mainland in the northwest, picking
up moisture over the South China Sea and Pacific
Ocean, and bringing the monsoon. But during the
dry season from April to September, the winds
reverse direction and blow from the southeast
and the deserts of Australia, bringing dry air
and a lower probability of rain. This meant you
could travel whichever direction you wanted, so
long as you wisely chose your season to sail.
As their confidence grew on the waves,
we have evidence that the Javanese also
undertook some even more ambitious voyages.
One Italian explorer who arrived in Java around
1505, named Ludovico Di Varthema of Bologna,
sailed to the island of Java, and was amazed to
see the captain of the ship navigate even when
the North Star was no longer visible. When the
chartered vessel was supplied with provisions,
we took our way towards the beautiful island
called Java, at which we arrived in five days,
sailing towards the south. My companion asked the
Christians, "Now that we have lost the North Star,
how does he steer us? Is there any other
North Star than this by which we steer?"
The Christians asked the captain of the ship this
same thing, and he showed us four or five stars,
among which there was one which he said
was the opposite to our North Star.
This was the so-called Southern Cross,
the distinctive pattern of stars that
could be seen in the southern hemisphere in the
direction of the South Pole. The Europeans were
amazed at this discovery, but the captain
then told him that the Javanese had sailed
into the south following these stars, and
had there come upon an icy and frozen land.
He also told us that on the other side of
the said island towards the south there
are some other races who navigate by the
said four or five stars opposite to ours,
and moreover, they gave us to understand that
beyond the said island, the day does not last
more than four hours, and that there it was
colder than in any other part of the world.
If this is true, it means that the Javanese
had already sailed to and around Australia,
and set out into the Antarctic Ocean.
But tantalizingly, we have only this
secondhand story to go by, and the rest
will have to be left to our imaginations.
But as the centuries of the first millennium
went on, there is a great deal more evidence
that the people of Java were making
their mark in even further lands.
7,000 kilometers away on
the shores of East Africa,
the 10th-century Persian writer Buzurg
Ibn Shahriyar gives an account of a series
of raids undertaken by a people from a
faraway land that he calls the Wakwak.
The Wakwak set out with a thousand ships to launch
a determined attack upon the town of Kanbaloh, but
they were unable to capture it, for the town was
strongly fortified and was surrounded by an arm of
the sea, in the midst of which Kanbaloh rose like
a fortress. When the people of the African coast
eventually came to terms with the attackers, they
learned more about why they had come and how far
they had traveled. The people of that country
demanded why they had come to Kanbaloh rather
than to any other place. They replied that it was
because the country possessed merchandise of value
in the Wakwak country and in China, such as ivory,
tortoiseshell, panther skins, and ambergris,
and also because they wanted to obtain some
of the Zenj people, who, being strong men,
are able to stand heavy labor. Their voyage,
they said, had lasted a year. If the story told
by these people be true, this proves that the
Wakwak islands are situated opposite to China.
The location of these Wakwak
islands has long been debated.
One clue can be found in the
Persian chronicler Ibn Khordadbeh,
whose description has made many historians believe
that they may have been the islands of Indonesia.
East of China are the lands of Wakwak, which are
so rich in gold that the inhabitants make the
chains for their dogs and the collars for their
monkeys of this metal. They manufacture tunics
woven with gold. Excellent ebony wood is found
there. Gold and ebony are exported from Wakwak.
This detail of dogs wearing collars made of
gold was also mentioned by early European
explorers who visited Java, leading many to
conclude that the Wakwak really were Javanese.
If this story does relate an attack on
Eastern Africa by the people of Java,
then it shows the extent of their
shipbuilding and seafaring prowess,
and that they had become a formidable
threat for all the peoples who lived
around the Indian Ocean. From these raids,
they would have brought back gold, ivory,
and slaves to Java. But in other places,
they didn't simply raid and sail away.
In the large island of Madagascar, just off the
coast of Eastern Africa, the people's language
has always puzzled linguists. The Madagascan
language of Malagasy shares little in common
with those of the African mainland, and
it was only when the grammar and syntax
were compared with Indonesian languages
that a remarkable similarity was noticed.
Although separated by the entire Indian Ocean,
the language of Malagasy shares a grammatical
structure with several Indonesian languages like
Javanese, and they even have a number of different
words in common. Just one example is the word for
island; nosee in Malagasy and nusa in Javanese.
In fact, the closest living relative of Malagasy
is thought to be a language called Maanyan,
which originated on the south coast of Borneo.
The most modern analysis of mitochondrial DNA in
Madagascar has confirmed this connection,
and shows that the people there can trace
their lineage back to about thirty mothers who
arrived on the island from what is now Indonesia.
This suggests a single boatload of settlers
who had traveled across one of the world's
widest oceans to find a new home. They also
brought plants and crops with them. Botanists
estimate that a full 7% of the plant life on
Madagascar today originated in Indonesia. These
include bananas, plantains, taro, and yams,
and all of these were already well established
there by the medieval period. In 1602, another
Portuguese explorer, Diogo do Couto, described
these far-reaching journeys of the Javanese. The
Javanese are all men very experienced in the art
of navigation, to the point that they claim
to be the most ancient of all. It is certain
that they formally navigated to Africa's Cape
of Good Hope, and were in communication with
the east coast of the island of Madagascar,
where there are many brown and Javanese-like
natives who say they are descended from them. The
Javanese of this period navigated using the stars,
but also magnetic compasses and maps written
on the bark of the paper mulberry tree.
In 1512, only twenty years after Columbus
had first reached the Americas, and twelve
years after the first Europeans set foot in
Brazil, a Portuguese conquistador fighting
on the Malay Peninsula captured a
sea chart from a Javanese sailor.
He was amazed to find that it had already been
updated with all the new discoveries that had
been made on the other side of the world, as he
wrote in one letter to King Manuel I of Portugal.
We found a large map of a Javanese pilot
containing the Cape of Good Hope, Portugal,
and the land of Brazil, the Red Sea and
the Sea of Persia, the Clove Islands,
the navigation of the Chinese and Japanese, and
how the kingdoms border on each other. It seems
to me, sir, that this was the best thing I
have ever seen, and your highness will be
very pleased to see it. In 2003, a modern team
was able to pilot a replica of an old Javanese
sailing ship from Indonesia to Madagascar and
around the Cape of Good Hope in South Africa,
thus proving that this journey was possible
with the technology available at the time.
But despite its remarkable achievements in
architecture and its voyages of discovery,
the Shailendra dynasty of Mataram
would eventually decline, and all
of its grand monuments would decline with it.
The reasons for the fall of Mataram are unclear,
since no true chronicles have survived from
this time. But the kingdom's decline may have
been related to a series of dramatic volcanic
eruptions that occurred sometime in
the 10th and early 11th centuries.
The people of Java have always lived with a
particular paradox, that the immense productivity
of their land also comes from its most destructive
force. Many landscapes that experience a monsoon
season as heavy as Java can suffer from poor soil
quality, as the seasonal rains wash away topsoil
and leech nutrients away. But in much of Java,
the hundreds of active volcanoes counteract this
effect. Due to the island's particular geology,
its volcanoes are especially beneficial for the
soil, filling it with minerals like magnesium,
potassium, and phosphorus that plants thrive on,
all blasted out of the depths of the earth
itself. Volcanic soil is also uniquely porous,
and retains moisture exceptionally well, while
allowing air circulation for plant roots.
But of course, a volcano is a violent phenomenon.
When they erupt, they scorch the earth with
pyroclastic flows, spew lava, and rain huge
boulders down from the sky across a large area.
This poses an obvious problem, that the areas of
the greatest agricultural productivity on
the island were also the most dangerous.
This meant that while the volcanoes overall
effect was positive, a year in which a great
eruption took place could wipe out a good
proportion of any kingdom's food supplies.
And of all these volcanoes, by
far the most active was the one
that the Javanese call by a name which
means the Mountain of Fire, or Merapi.
Rising to nearly 3,000 meters or 10,000
feet, Mount Merapi is the most active
volcano in the whole of Indonesia, and
is considered one of the most active
and dangerous in the world. It has erupted
regularly for at least the last 500 years,
with small eruptions occurring every two to three
years, and larger ones every ten to fifteen.
Then every few hundred years, the mountain
explodes in a truly catastrophic fashion.
The Javanese Chronicle, the Babad Tanah
Jawi, records the devastation caused by one
eruption of the great Mount Merapi that took
place in the 16th century. Then Mount Merapi
erupted with fire. It made a terrifying thundering
noise. A rain of ash fell. A volcanic mudflow ran
down the Ompak River. Big rocks rose from the
flow and landed on the land. When the piles of
wood on the Gunung Kidul mountains were set on
fire, the mountains became a blaze of fire. The
Gong Kyai Bicak was beaten ceaselessly. All tried
to save their lives and ran in all directions.
Added to this obvious physical destruction,
the Javanese also held the volcanoes in
great spiritual reverence, and viewed
eruptions as signs and portents from the
gods. After the deaths of great kings,
Javanese chronicles often describe the
mountains rumbling in mourning. At the death
of his majesty, the wailing in the palace was
as loud as thunder. Mount Merapi rumbled,
joining in with the sound of a rainstorm.
It was believed that the eruptions, earthquakes,
and various rumblings of the land were not just
seismic events, but actually one of the primary
ways that the gods weighed in on the affairs
of humanity. For this reason, their timing
could have real life-or-death consequences.
One chronicle recounts the story of a lucky
prisoner held by a 17th-century Javanese king.
The king wanted to kill the prisoner Raden
Mas Surya-ku-suma, but this did not happen,
because every time they wanted to kill him,
Mount Merapi flared up with a terrifying noise.
In the end, the man was set free and promoted
and given the lordship of 1,000 rice fields.
A particularly devastating eruption would not
only cause immense economic damage to the kingdom;
it could also be considered a clear sign
that the gods were angry with the current
ruler. For any king who didn't have a firm
grasp on power, this could be a devastating
blow. From some inscriptions left in Java, we
know that as the 9th century came to an end,
the kingdom of Mataram descended into civil
war, with three kings ruling in only two years.
When the dust of this civil war settled
in the year 929, a king named Rake Hino
pu Sindok took to the throne. But curiously,
it seems the kingdom of Mataram had by this
point moved. All of the inscriptions issued
by this king would be written in East Java,
far away from its original heartlands
around the volcano Mount Merapi.
It seems that around the beginning of the 10th
century, the entire Mataram kingdom simply upped
sticks and fled its original wealthy province,
leaving its towering temples and cities abandoned,
and what's perhaps most significant is
that no other power seems to have swept
in to the empty lands. This suggests that
some kind of cataclysm took place there.
Archaeological evidence shows that the early
10th-century layer of human occupation at the
great temple of Borobudur, for instance, is
sealed by up to half a meter of volcanic ash,
suggesting a major eruption. The peoples of this
land were no strangers to erupting volcanoes,
so we can imagine that it must have taken
one of particular violence or a series of
eruptions taking place in frighteningly quick
succession to cause the wholesale abandonment
of this kingdom and its reestablishment
hundreds of kilometers to the east.
One inscription known as the Pucangan Stone
describes a kind of disaster sweeping the land.
In the time of the great catastrophe
that overwhelmed the island of Java in
the Saka year 928, when King Wurawari came forth
from Lwaram, the whole of Java seemed
transformed into a single raging sea.
Many of the foremost men of the realm perished.
Chief among the dead was the divine king.
Unfortunately, the exact dating of
volcanic eruptions is difficult,
and it's hard to say whether this was
truly the cause of Mataram's downfall.
But whether from volcanic causes or not,
it's clear that for one reason or another,
life had become unlivable for the
people of Mataram in Central Java.
The kingdom eventually reached a level of
stability in its new home in East Java,
away from the destruction it had faced,
but its confidence in itself and in the
gods approval of its rulers had been
fatally reduced. Within a century,
the remains of Mataram was facing destruction,
now at the hands of human enemies.
An invasion by a neighboring king wiped out
what was left of it, and the kingdom of Mataram
disappeared, living on only in the stone carvings
left lining the walls of its great temples,
thousands of moments of everyday life now
sealed beneath a thick layer of volcanic ash.
After the fall of Mataram, a number of successor
kingdoms would rise up. In the 11th century,
much of Java was reunited again under
the rule of a king named Airlangga,
whose name meant he who leapt over the water
. He was born on the small island of Bali,
and crossed the sea to Java as a young
man. The Pucangan Stone describes how this
king was spared from the destruction that
swept the land during the fall of Mataram.
At that time, his majesty was only sixteen
years old, still too young to have mastered
the art of war. Yet, because he was
the very manifestation of Vishnu,
all the gods protected him from being
swept away by the great destruction.
Airlangga would rule successfully for
several decades, but when he died,
the land divided again. The kingdom that
would truly give birth to Java's golden
era was named Singhasari. Singhasari derived its
name from the Sanskrit word simha , meaning lion,
and this lion kingdom was founded
by a king named Ken Angrok.
Ken Angrok's name means the man who overturned
everything , and he was a revolutionary force on
Java. In the centuries since he lived,
the legend of Ken Angrok has grown to
mythic proportions, and he has inspired
theater, song, and poetry in Indonesia.
The story of his life is largely told in a
fragmentary chronicle known as the Pararaton,
or the Book of Kings, written sometime later in
the 16th century. According to this chronicle,
Ken Angrok was actually the son of the
Hindu god Brahma, who appeared to his
mother, a poor woman named Ken Endok, and
informed her of her immaculate conception.
The god Brahma descended there and lay with Ken
Endok. This meeting took place in the fields of
Lalaten. The god made a vow with the woman.
You must not go to your husband again. If you
lie with him, he will die, and my child will
be corrupted. That child is named Ken Angrok,
and he will one day rule the land
of Java. With that, Brahma vanished.
The woman held true to her word, and soon Ken
Angrok was born. But the family was extremely
poor and couldn't provide for the little boy.
His parents abandoned him in a grave, but he was
found by a common thief named Lembong, who was
perhaps plundering the graveyard for valuables.
When her time was full, she gave birth
to a boy. Ken Endok abandoned him in a
burial ground for children. Not long
after, a thief named Lembong wandered
into the same place. There he saw
something glowing. Drawn to it,
he heard the sound of a child crying. When he
came closer, he saw that the light was coming
from the child himself. Lembong picked him up,
carried him home, and raised him as his own son.
Brought up by this thief, Ken Angrok would
learn all the tricks of his trade until he
was the most accomplished thief in Java. But one
day he met an Indian holy man who identified him
as the son of Brahma and an embodiment of the god
Vishnu. This holy man convinced Ken Angrok to give
up his sinful life. As a reward, Ken Angrok
gained a magical weapon, a kind of Javanese
knife known as a keris. These are long daggers
often created with a distinctive rippled blade,
and they were worn by Javanese men as a sign
of status, as a talisman against various evils,
and of course as a practical sidearm for
self-defense. One Chinese visitor to Java
at the start of the 15th century named Ma Huan
writes about the importance of these blades.
From little boys of three years to old men of
a hundred years, they all have these knives,
which are all made of steel, with most intricate
patterns drawn in very delicate lines. For the
handles, they use gold or rhinoceros
horn or elephants teeth engraved with
representations of human forms or devils faces,
the craftsmanship being very fine and skilful.
With this magical sword by his side,
Ken Angrok rose to prominence in Java,
and eventually, through the overwhelming force of
his various virtues, became its
king, as the Pararaton describes.
Not long afterwards, Ken Angrok was acclaimed
as king of Tumapel. His realm was called
Singhasari. His enthronement was witnessed by
learned men of both the Shaivite and Buddhist
traditions of Kediri. Those who had once
shown Ken Angrok kindness in his days of
hardship were summoned, granted protection,
and generously rewarded for their loyalty.
Not everyone easily accepted the rule of this
commoner. In the nearby rival kingdom of Kediri,
the king was named Dandhang Gendis, and he
refused to accept Ken Angrok as his king.
Dandhang Gendis gathered his armies
and marched to fight Ken Angrok,
but he was no match for the
divine power of the god made man.
He fell because he was attacked on all sides
by the forces of Singhasari, who came on like
a flood pouring down from the mountains. The army
of Kediri scattered like a swarm of bees, fleeing
in panic, abandoning the field like startled
goats, casting aside their parasols. King Dandhang
Gendis withdrew from the battle and fled into the
realm of the gods, rising up into the air with his
horse, his grooms, his parasol-bearers, and those
who carried his drinking vessels and his mats,
all of them ascending into the sky. Thus,
Kediri was utterly defeated by Ken Angrok.
Needless to say, this section of the Pararaton
Chronicle is considered to be largely mythical,
and reflects the propaganda of this
king's new regime. But this story
would be repeated across the towns and
villages of Java by trained storytellers,
who together wove a new national myth around
the figure of Ken Angrok. One of the most
important mediums in which this story was
told was that of the Javanese shadow puppets.
The exact origin of Javanese shadow puppetry
is a mystery, but it's clear from a number of
oblique references in Javanese literature that
it was already a well-established practice by
at least the 10th century. This form of
shadow theater is known as wayang. Wayang
in Javanese means shadow or ghost , but
it can also mean imagination , and these
plays would retell stories from the Hindu
epics like the Mahabharat, local Javanese
stories such as how rice came to the earth,
and the stories of their kings and ancestors.
The Chinese visitor to Java at
the beginning of the 15th century,
Ma Huan, describes witnessing these performances.
Each time the performer unrolls and exposes a
section of the picture, he thrusts it forward
toward the audience, and speaking with a loud
voice in the foreign language, he explains
the derivation of this section. The crowd sits
around and listens to him, sometimes laughing,
sometimes crying, exactly as if the narrator
were reciting one of our popular romances.
These shadow plays would typically
start at nightfall and go on until dawn,
and would be conducted behind a screen of
white cotton fabric using a lamp burning
with coconut oil, usually cast in metal
in the form of the sacred bird garuda.
The puppets were typically made of goat hide
or buffalo skin, mounted on bamboo canes,
and placed in a trunk of banana palm lying
behind the screen. The puppets had jointed
limbs and were punctured all over with intricate
patterns of holes that allowed the light through
so that their shadows could then be cast onto a
screen. These puppet shows were often accompanied
by music. In small village performances, this
could simply be the drumming of the puppeteer
on the box where the puppets were kept. But
in the royal court, a puppeteer would perform
alongside a full orchestra of musicians known as a
gamelan, with a whole host of fifteen instruments.
These night-long plays would unfold according to
strict traditions. In the hours between sunset
and midnight, the puppeteer introduced the
characters and set up the conflict, and then
at the stroke of midnight, the drama burst out
into a frenzied clash between good and evil.
The Portuguese traveller and apothecary Tom Pires,
who visited Java around 1513, wrote about seeing
these forms of theater and shadow puppetry.
The land of Java is a land of performers and
masks of various Javanese kinds, and both men
and women do thus. They have entertainments of
dancing and stories. They mime. They wear actors
dresses and all their clothes. They are certainly
graceful. They have music of bells. The sound of
all of them playing together is like an organ.
These actors show a thousand graces like these
by day and night. At night, they make shadows
of various shapes. Over time, the performance of
these shadow plays took on a spiritual meaning.
The puppeteer, or dalang, was thought to become
possessed by the power of the gods as he worked,
and in the performance, all the holy elements
were represented; the banana palm representing the
earth, the cloth screen the sky, the fire in the
coconut oil lamp, and of course, the interplay of
light and darkness, good and evil, as the stories
of gods and demons played out across the screen.
These performances were
considered to have real power.
Some such as the Brata Yudha, or a Javanese
version of the Indian epic the Mahabharat, were
considered too potent to ever perform in their
entirety, as Thomas Stamford Raffles records.
Although the wayang may represent
any portion of the Brata Yudha,
there is a prevalent superstition that
a great war will be the inevitable
consequence of performing at one
sitting the whole of this poem.
It is gravely asserted that a chief of Kendal
tried this experiment about fifty years ago,
but that the performance was no sooner completed
than his country was laid to waste and destroyed.
Other of these shadow plays were performed
at auspicious times in order to bring
about certain effects, with stories of the
goddess of rice told during the harvests,
and the great myths told during times of
trouble and strife. One particular shadow
play was reserved solely for times when a plague
of mice or rats had descended on a village,
and its goal was to convince the rodents to
depart and dwell in the kingdom of vermin instead.
Over the next centuries, the story of Ken Angrok,
the first king of Singhasari, would be told again
and again in these kinds of performances, and
would take on more and more fantastical elements;
and for that reason, it's impossible to say
definitively which parts may have a grain of
truth to them. But it's likely that some
elements are true, that Ken Angrok was a
common man of uncertain birth and lineage, that
he had been a thief or brigand of some kind,
that he rose to power in the kingdom in a violent
upheaval, and crushed the nearby kingdom of Kediri
in open battle. But after he comes to the throne,
the tone of the chronicle shifts and becomes more
grounded in historical reality. Many events
recorded during his reign are dated, and so
this second half of the chronicle is considered to
contain more historically verifiable information.
What we know for sure is that over
the course of the 13th century,
Ken Angrok's new kingdom of Singhasari
would gradually expand its power, wealth,
and prestige. But it was under the reign of his
great grandson, the fifth king of Singhasari,
that it would grow into a true empire. His name
was King Kertanegara, and during his time on the
throne, he would order expeditions to extend the
kingdom's influence not just over most of Java,
but across the sea to the large island of Borneo
to the north, the small island of Bali to the
east, and even conduct a successful invasion of
Java's sister island of Sumatra in the northwest.
Now the kingdom of Singhasari had
grown to be a true seagoing empire,
and it controlled virtually all of
the region's most crucial waterways,
and the most important of these was the narrow
sea corridor known as the Strait of Malacca.
The Malay Peninsula is a long body of land
that stretches southeast from the southern
edge of the Asian continent where Thailand meets
Malaysia, and just off its southernmost point and
following the line of the continental shelf is
the island of Sumatra and then Java. Together,
these form a sea wall of more than 3,000
kilometers that stands between the Indian
Ocean and the South Pacific and South China
Sea. In this massive wall, there are only
two narrow gates, the southerly one known as
the Straits of Sunda, and the northern one,
the Straits of Malacca. The American sailor and
writer Herman Melville, writing in the mid 19th
century, describes the sight of these straits.
Those narrow Straits of Sunda stand midway in
that vast rampart of islands like the central
gateway opening into some vast, walled empire.
The inexhaustible wealth of spices and silks and
jewels and gold and ivory, with which the thousand
islands of that oriental sea are enriched, are
thus guarded from the all-grasping Western world.
For much of history, it has been the wider and
deeper Strait of Malacca that has been used most
heavily. In fact, today it is the busiest shipping
channel in the world, seeing nearly 100,000 ships
pass through it each year. Around a quarter of all
global trade passes through this narrow waterway,
where the massive cities of Singapore and Kuala
Lumpur are today located. And in the 13th century,
during the time of the Singhasari kingdom, this
waterway was no less crucial or lucrative. Around
the year 1515, the Portuguese diplomat Tom Pires
passed through the Yemeni port of Aden on the Red
Sea, and wrote that goods transported thousands
of miles from Malacca featured prominently in
the city's markets, where merchants would carry
them on to Egypt, and from there into Europe.
The merchants from Cairo bring the merchandise
which comes from Italy and Greece and Damascus
to Aden, while the merchants of Aden take back
with them all the products of Malacca; cloves,
nutmeg, mace, sandalwood, brazilwood, silks,
seed pearls, musk, porcelain, and other things.
Control of the narrow waterway of the Malacca
strait gave King Kertanegara immense power,
despite the relatively small size of the
kingdom of Singhasari. Now, anyone wishing
to sail between China and India or the rest of the
world either did so with Kertanegara's permission,
or had to take a detour of at least 2,000
kilometers through rough and stormy seas around
this island wall. As a result of this control, the
power and wealth of Singhasari grew dramatically.
But there were much larger empires in the region
who had a strong interest in making sure that
the flow of goods by sea could pass through these
narrow straits. And as the 13th century came to an
end, the kingdom of Singhasari came into direct
conflict with one of these much larger powers.
In the year 1289, King Kertanegara of the Javanese
kingdom of Singhasari received a
group of ambassadors at his court.
They came finely dressed, haughty and proud,
and said that they had come to speak on behalf
of the world's most powerful man. That was
the Mongol emperor of China, Kublai Khan.
As we saw in our 19th episode, from their
humble beginnings on the Mongolian steppe,
over the last century, the Mongols had embarked on
a remarkable series of campaigns to conquer all of
China, Persia, and the Middle East, along with
much of what is today Russia and Eastern Europe.
Founded by the warlord Chinggis Khan, the Mongol
Empire was the largest contiguous land empire
in history, and combined the speed and power
of Mongol horsemen with the craftsmanship of
Persia and the ingenuity and manpower of China. By
this point, the enormous Mongol Empire had split
into four separate domains, but the largest of
these was still the world's biggest empire at the
time. That was the one ruled from China by the
grandson of Chinggis Khan, the emperor Kublai.
This hybrid Chinese-Mongolian power was known as
the Yuan Dynasty. But by this time, the empire
had begun to struggle. The emperor Kublai was
now well into his seventies, and his domain
was plagued by political and economic problems.
The Mongol Empire had been built on conquest,
but now its terrifying engine seemed to have
run out of fuel. Eight years earlier, Kublai's
forces had for the second time failed to capture a
foothold on the islands of Japan. His invasions of
Burma and Vietnam had also fizzled out, with the
Mongol forces struggling in the tropical heat.
The aging Mongol emperor desperately needed a
victory, and he had been increasingly casting
his gaze southwards, across the sea, and
towards the wealthy island of Java. The
Chinese chronicle the Yuanshi, or History of
Yuan, describes this strange and faraway land.
The customs and products of this land are not
much known, but as a rule, the barbarian countries
over the sea produce many rare and valuable
things which fetch a high price in China.
The inhabitants are strange, and their nature
and speech are not understood by the Chinese.
By that time, Java's King Kertanegara had
been defying Kublai Khan for nearly a decade.
Two previous ambassadorial visits to his court had
been sent home without any tribute for the Mongol
Khan, and the defiance of this small island
was beginning to make the empire look weak.
For this reason, in 1289, Kublai sent
a new party of envoys to Java to meet
with the king and give him a final
ultimatum. They demanded that King
Kertanegara swear an oath of fealty to the
Mongol emperor, pay him a hefty tribute,
and send members of his royal family to the
Mongol court in China to act as hostages.
But when these ambassadors arrived, they would
not find King Kertanegara in an agreeable mood.
The Javanese of the time considered
repeated requests of this kind to be
exceedingly rude. Tom Pires writes about
the proud nature of the Javanese people.
The Javanese are men who, if they
write once and do not get a reply,
do not write again, although it may be of
great importance to them. The Javanese are
daring men and determined to die. They
are gamblers and play for high stakes.
King Kertanegara was no different, and he would
now make a tremendous gamble for the highest
stakes possible. He ordered that the Mongol
ambassadors be punished. By some accounts,
their faces were branded with
hot irons and their ears cut off,
a punishment typically reserved
for bandits and pirates.
We can only imagine the rage of the Mongol
emperor Kublai Khan upon hearing this news
and seeing the mutilated faces of his ambassadors.
The History of Yuan describes what happened next.
In the second month of the 29th year of the
Yuan Dynasty, the emperor issued an order
to the governor of Fujian, directing
him to send an army to subdue Java,
to collect soldiers to the number of
20,000, to send out a thousand ships,
and to equip them with provisions for
a year, and with 40,000 bars of silver.
The emperor said to them, "When you arrive at
Java, you must clearly proclaim that they have
lately cut the face of the imperial envoy, Meng
Chi, and that you have come to punish them."
This expedition set sail three years later in the
year 1292, but it was to be a difficult voyage.
The History of Yuan describes the troubles
they encountered on the Java Sea. The wind
was strong and the sea very rough, so that the
ships rolled heavily and the soldiers could
not eat for many days. The forces to attack
Java were driven by the wind to one island,
and many ships were wrecked.
Over a hundred men who were
ill from the long beating about in the storm were
unable to leave with the rest of the expedition,
and were left there. And today, the Chinese
live mixed up with the native families.
Despite their troubles on the voyage,
the Mongol forces eventually arrived on
the shores of Java in the next year of 1293,
ready to punish King Kertanegara for defying
the empire and mistreating its ambassadors.
But when they arrived, they would find their
enthusiasm for revenge had been somewhat
deflated. In fact, in the preceding year,
the defiant King Kertanegara had been overthrown
and killed by a usurper named Jaya-Katong.
Jaya-Katong was the ruler of a city called Kediri,
which controlled a province covering much of
Central Java. For a long time, Kediri had actually
been the predominant power on the island, but
after its king, Dandan Gendhis, had been defeated
in battle by the hero Ken Angrok, Kediri had been
eclipsed by the rise of Singhasari. Now Kediri was
a vassal of King Kertanegara, but it was by far
the most powerful of his subjects, and as a result
never sat comfortably within his kingdom. The epic
poem the Deshawarnana describes the new ruler of
Kediri, Jaya-Katong, as cunning and malevolent.
There was a vassal king, a villain known
by the name of Jaya-Katong, who there,
in the land of Kediri, desired to replace the king
and was outstandingly clever at laying schemes.
At the time, the majority of King
Kertanegara's forces were away from Java,
fighting to increase his territory
across the sea in Sumatra. And so,
Jaya-Katong saw his chance. According to the
Pararaton or Book of Kings, Jaya-Katong was
encouraged to seize the opportunity by one of
his allies, who sent him a thinly-veiled message.
The secret letter said, "My
lord, I respectfully tell you,
if his majesty has any consideration and desire
to hunt, now his majesty has the chance to so
hunt. It will be the best and the most opportune
moment. There is no danger. There are no tigers,
wild buffaloes, nor snakes, or even thorns.
There is only one tiger, but it has no teeth.
Urged on by this coded message, King Jaya-Katong
rose in rebellion. His city of Kediri was not far
from the capital of Singhasari, but it was on
the other side of a number of towering volcanic
cones, mounts Kelud, Arjuna, and Kawi. To
strike at Singhasari and depose the king,
he could either march north through the
easier territory of the northern plains,
or south through the rugged hill country riven
by gorges and ravines. The cunning Jaya-Katong
considered his options and came up with a plan.
In 1292, alarming news reached King Kertanegara's
court. Messengers would have burst into his
throne room and breathlessly told him that an
army had been seen rampaging through the farmland
to the north, flying the distinctive white and red
banners of Kediri. They had taken the toothless
tiger King Kertanegara completely by surprise.
Now, King Jaya-Katong set out to
attack. His army, coming from the north,
consisted of bad people. They were full of flags
and sounds. The area to the north was devastated.
Dismayed at the destruction, the king
appointed one of his son-in-laws to
lead what forces he had remaining
in Java, a man named Raden Wijaya.
This young man marched north with
the remains of the royal army,
and met Jaya-Katong's rampaging forces in battle,
as one Javanese inscription carved at a place
called Kudadu describes. When King Jaya-Katong's
troops reached the village of Jasun-Wungkal,
King Kertanegara sent his son-in-law, Raden
Wijaya, to fight the enemy. After the battle,
the enemy fled while suffering a great
loss. Seemingly they disappeared forever.
Raden Wijaya had succeeded in the north
and defended his father-in-law's kingdom,
which he was set to one day inherit. But now
the true strategy of Jaya-Katong was revealed.
While this loud northern force had been burning
and sacking their way through the north of the
kingdom, a much larger second force had also
advanced in the south. This army moved much
more stealthily through the ravines and valleys of
the central highlands, as the Pararaton describes.
Then a large army descended from Kediri,
coming from the banks of the Aksa River,
heading towards Lawor. They were not
allowed to carry flags or make any
noise. Upon arrival at Sidabawana,
they headed straight for Singhasari.
This force would go completely unnoticed, and they
apparently arrived at the kingdom's capital
of Kutaraja while King Kertanegara was drunk.
Drinking in Java was a serious business,
and a large number of alcoholic beverages
were consumed for pleasure, especially on
special occasions. One Javanese poem known
as the Sumanasaantaka describes the drinks
available at an idealized wedding. The drinks
poured continuously from rock crystal pitches
like fountains of palm syrup. Sugar cane, wine,
and rice beer were drunk one after the other like
holy water and mead welling up from glass vessels.
But the influence of tantric Buddhism meant
that drinking was more than just for fun.
In fact, it was at times a spiritual practice, and
even a royal duty. The king was required to take
part in ceremonies known as chakra-puja,
which involved the drawing of geometric
designs on the earth with colored powder,
after which the ritual could take place.
The historian Miranda Shaw describes
the unfolding of one of these rituals.
An elaborate array of offerings and foods are laid
out. The participants don special insignia-like
bone ornaments and crowns, and use musical
instruments of archaic design such as skull drums,
thighbone trumpets, and conch horns for inducing
heightened awareness. Practitioners sit in a
circle and partake of sacramental meat and wine
served in skull cups. The feast culminates in
the performance of tantric dances and music
that must never be disclosed to outsiders.
While this ceremony was a crucial part
of King Kertanegara's royal calendar,
the timing couldn't have been worse. Jaya-Katong's
concealed force arrived outside the city walls
without warning. They took the garrison by
surprise, and poured over the walls of the
city while the king was thus engaged. The city
was taken, and King Kertanegara was killed.
The king's son-in-law, Raden Wijaya, was
still celebrating his victory in the north,
and he must have been distraught when the news
reached him. He had won his battle, but lost the
war, and now everything he had stood to inherit
had also been taken by the usurper Jaya-Katong.
Raden Wijaya now retreated to
the rainforests of the northeast,
and left the capital and the throne in the hands
of the rebel Jaya-Katong. The city of Kutaraja,
the heart of the Singhasari kingdom, was looted
and depopulated, and many of its people taken
back to Kediri. Others simply fled into the
safety of the countryside and never returned.
Some stonemasons working on a new temple
in the city simply dropped their tools
in the middle of carving their reliefs, and
never came back to finish them. After that,
the city was left to crumble and be
taken over by the encroaching forest.
Now the dispossessed prince Raden Wijaya and
the rebel usurper Jaya-Katong faced off against
one another, but it seems neither side of
this civil war was confident in victory.
Raden Wijaya wasn't strong enough to march
south and take his enemy's capital of Kediri,
and meanwhile, Jaya-Katong couldn't leave
his city and risk losing his shaky grasp on
the throne. Both parties entered into
an uneasy negotiation, and eventually
the rebel king settled for buying off Raden
Wijaya. In exchange for laying down his arms,
the prince would be granted a piece of land,
and there he would be allowed to build a city.
Raden Wijaya, now completely out of other
options and stranded in the wild rainforest,
had no choice but to agree, but it must have
been with no small amount of bitterness.
The prince must have felt bitter, too, when he
reached the piece of land that Jaya-Katong had
granted him. It was a wild overgrown jungle
in the middle of a sparsely-inhabited area
known as the Tarik Forest. But his fate was
sealed, and he swallowed his bitterness and
ordered his people to begin clearing
the land for construction and farming.
The old growth forests of Java were dense and
wild, fed by the volcanic soil. Colorful hornbills
roosted in the treetops, while hidden high among
the branches, gibbons greeted the rising sun with
their long, mournful songs. Troops of long-tailed
macaque monkeys leapt through the trees,
while sambar deer crept through the shade of the
forest. Great pythons lay coiled in the trees,
and dangerous animals like the Javan leopard and
wild boar lurked hidden in the green undergrowth.
Everywhere could be heard the creaking of
cicadas and frogs calling to one another
from hidden pools. At sunset, fruit bats rose
in their thousands from their hidden caves,
while fireflies would have been visible at
night. The trees were the most ancient life
of the forest. Towering hardwoods like teak,
ebony, and tamarind would have risen here,
interspersed with bamboo groves, strangler
figs, palms, and tangled liana vines,
all competing for every shaft of sunlight.
But when they began cutting down this forest,
Raden Wijaya's men found that a particular
kind of tree grew there in great quantities.
This was the tree that grows a fruit which in
Indonesia is called maja, and is known elsewhere
as a wood apple, elephant apple, or Indian quince.
These maja fruits are pear-shaped and the size of
a large grapefruit, with a thick, hard, woody
rind that needs to be cracked with a hammer.
Inside is an orangey-yellow pulp that gives off
the scent of roses but tastes sweet and bitter,
a little like marmalade. The word for
bitter in Javanese is pahit , and due
to the large numbers of these maja
fruits growing in this region,
the people named this place Majapahit, or
bitter wood apple, as the Pararaton describes.
When the Madurese were building the village, a
hungry man, lacking supplies while cutting down
the forest, ate a maja fruit. He found it bitter
and threw away all the maja fruit he had picked.
The maja fruit there became known for its bitter
taste, and the place was then named Majapahit.
For Raden Wijaya and his people, the name
Majapahit was a perfect encapsulation of the
bitterness of their situation. They had lost
a kingdom and gained a plot of wild jungle in
return, and all because of the treachery
of Jaya-Katong. They all must have shared
a single desire; to throw out the rebel king
and unite Java once more. Their chance would
come in the year 1293, when the sails of
the Mongol fleet appeared on the horizon.
The Mongol fleet that had been sent
to punish the people of Java was led
by a commander named Shih-bi. When he
heard of the death of King Kertanegara,
he must have found himself in a quandary.
His emperor demanded vengeance, and he and
his men had sailed for months to get there. He
must have feared leaving empty-handed. It was
while he was puzzling over this situation that
Shih-bi was approached by a messenger from the
bitter lord of the new city of Majapahit,
the dispossessed prince Raden Wijaya.
The Chinese History of Yuan describes
the deal that the Mongols struck.
At that time, Java carried on an old
feud with the neighboring country,
and the old king of Java had already been killed.
The son-in-law of the former, Raden Wijaya,
had attacked Jaya-Katong,
but could not overcome him.
He therefore retired to Majapahit, and when he
heard that Shih-bi and his army had arrived,
he sent envoys with an account of his rivers
and seaports and a map of the country, offering
his submission and asking for assistance.
Shih-bi then advanced with all his forces.
For the Mongols, the arrangement was
a neat way to solve their problem.
They would help Raden Wijaya overthrow the rebel
Jaya-Katong, and place him on the throne as a
kind of puppet king, swearing allegiance to the
Mongols in China. Then Shih-bi could return to
Kublai Khan and say that he had brought the
defiant little island back under control.
But among Raden Wijaya's men, it must have been a
controversial proposal. The Javanese were a proud
people, and few had any desire to be ruled by
the far-off Mongol Emperor. Some may even have
called Raden Wijaya a coward and a traitor. But
all this time, he was hatching a plot of his own.
The later chronicle of the Pararaton describes the
ensuing war, referring to the Mongols as Tatars.
The Tatar army came out from the north, while
the Majapahit armies came out from the east.
King Jaya-Katong was confused, unsure which to
guard. Then he was attacked heavily from the
north by the Tatar army. King Jaya-Katong, who
was fighting to the north, armed with a shield,
was attacked together by the Tatar people, and
was finally caught and imprisoned by the Tatars.
The Mongols had now become kingmakers in
Java. The 13th-century Persian historian
Abdullah Wassaf describes how they put
Raden Wijaya on the Javanese throne.
His majesty Kublai put the old king's
son-in-law, Wijaya, on the steps of the
throne. He bestowed on him a ceremonial dress of
honor, and conferred on him much grace, and in
exchange for the payment of tribute and taxes of
pearls and gold, he left the island in his hands.
The Mongol emperor Kublai must have been
ecstatic when he heard the news. Finally,
here was a victory he could show to his people.
The wealthy island of Java would now be added
to his imperial domain, along with its control of
major shipping lanes, and perhaps now the fortunes
of his teetering empire would finally turn around.
But that was not to be the case. That's because
the new king, Raden Wijaya, had no intention
of ruling Java as a vassal of Kublai Khan,
and the moment he got to power, he turned on
the Mongol forces who had helped him seize
the throne. The Chinese History of Yuan gives
a terse account of this disastrous turnaround.
Raden Wijaya asked permission to return to
his country in order to prepare a new letter
of submission to the emperor, and to take the
precious articles in his possession back to court.
Shih-bi consented to this, and sent two officers
with 200 men to go with him. But on the way,
Raden Wijaya killed the two officers and
revolted again. After which, he availed
himself of the circumstance that the main army
was returning to attack it from both sides.
The Mongol army believed their mission to
be complete, and were already packing their
ships to leave. The seasonal winds were about to
change direction, and if they didn't move fast,
they might become stranded on Java for another
six months. When Raden Wijaya's soldiers burst out
of the forest in ambush, firing arrows and darts
from their blow guns, the Mongol Yuan troops were
taken completely by surprise. The Javanese epic
poem Bhomantaka describes a battle of this kind.
They were thrown into disarray, and in fear the
demon army fled, and many of the demons and their
leaders were struck dead. They withdrew in haste
to the shelter of the fort, but were pursued.
Others, shuddering, sought a way of resisting,
but lacked the strength and, hit by arrows,
floundered about, and all of them left in fear
and ran away. The whole fort was in uproar,
and all shouted in confusion. The fires glowed and
blazed up frightfully like an erupting volcano.
Thousands were killed, and the
remains of the Mongol army fled
in disarray back to the ships,
as the History of Yuan describes.
Shih-bi was left behind and was cut off from
the rest of the army. He was forced to fight
his way back to the ships for a distance of
more than 100 miles. At last, he embarked again,
and reached China on a voyage of sixty-eight days.
Of his soldiers, more than 3,000 men had died.
When news of this betrayal reached the emperor
Kublai Khan, we can only imagine his rage. He
ordered the general Shih-bi to receive seventeen
lashes, and commanded a third of his property to
be confiscated as punishment for his failure.
He ordered his ministers to begin immediate
preparations for a full-scale invasion of Java
with an even larger army of 100,000 men. But
these plans would never come to fruition. The
disaster in Java would be the last campaign of
Kublai Khan's reign, and he died the next year
in February of 1294 at the age of seventy-eight.
After that, the Mongol Yuan Dynasty would enter
into a steady and irrevocable decline, and would
collapse entirely little more than seventy years
later. One great empire was coming to an end,
but in its collapse, it gave way for the rise
of what was now the undisputed major power on
the island of Java and in the archipelago
of Nusantara, the new power of Majapahit.
On the 15th day of the month of Kaartikka,
the 8th month of the Hindu calendar,
Raden Wijaya was crowned king
in the palace of Majapahit.
What had once been a stretch of wild jungle
was now the beating heart of Java's most
powerful kingdom. The Chinese History of Sung
describes the appearance of the kings of Java,
and from this we might imagine how this new
king looked on the day of his coronation.
The king has hair in a knot upon the
top of his head. He wears golden bells,
a silk robe, and shoes of leather. He sits
on a square couch, and his functionaries,
who see him daily, salute him three
times on going away. When he goes out,
he rides on an elephant or sits in a carriage,
and from 500 to 700 soldiers follow him.
When the people see the king, they
squat down until he has passed.
Raden Wijaya would rule as the king
of Majapahit for sixteen years,
but his reign would be a troubled one.
From the earliest days of his
rule, he faced rebellions,
many of them from men who had fought alongside
him against Jaya-Katong and the Mongols.
Many of these disagreements were sparked over the
question of who would become the king's mahapatih,
a powerful and influential position that combined
elements of a prime minister and head general,
and essentially acted as the king's right hand.
Whatever his skills as a diplomat, it seems Raden
Wijaya struggled to manage the ambitions of the
men who served under him. For this reason, he
spent much of his rule putting down rebellions all
over Java. In an effort to cement the legitimacy
of his new dynasty, he would marry the remaining
three daughters of his dead father-in-law,
Kertanegara, and ensure that the royal line
of succession would pass entirely through him.
But still the problems persisted, and the new
kingdom teetered on the brink of destruction.
When Raden Wijaya died in the year 1309,
he must have hoped that his only son,
Jayanegara, would set things right. But
due to the apparently deficient nature
of Jayanegara's character,
this would not be the case.
King Jayanegara would rule for nearly
twenty years after the death of his father,
but he was a widely disliked character, so
much so that the author of the chronicle the
Pararaton would give him the nickname Kala
Gemet, meaning weak villain . Meanwhile,
the Javanese folk tradition has remembered
him by the name Bajang Ratu, or dwarf
king , referencing either his short stature
or simply the uninspiring nature of his rule.
Jayanegara faced multiple attempts on his life
and widespread rebellions even worse than his
father s, the most serious of which was led by a
man named Kuti. This uprising became so dangerous
that the king was forced to abandon his capital
for a time, and it's during this time of upheaval
that a man would walk onto the historical stage
who would turn around the fortunes of this new
and struggling kingdom. He was a soldier who led
the king's bodyguard during the Kuti rebellion,
and gained a position of trust in the
royal court. His name was Gajah Mada.
Gajah Mada's name came from the old Javanese word
gaja , meaning elephant , and mada , which is a
difficult to translate word describing a state
of furious intoxication. This probably alluded
to the period of a few weeks every year when male
elephants enter their breeding cycle called musth,
and their testosterone levels explode. During
this time, a bull elephant seeps liquid from a
gland around its ears, and becomes extremely
aggressive and dangerous. Elephants had long
been used for warfare in Java. They formed the
centerpiece of any army, and allowed royals
and generals to command the battlefield from an
elevated position. Although prehistoric fossils of
native elephants have been found in Java, this
species had long been extinct by this point,
and during the medieval period, elephants were
imported from other lands. They were enormous,
expensive, and prestigious, their tusks sometimes
adorned with metal implements to make them even
more deadly, and their sides often oiled before
going into battle to prevent the enemy from
climbing on their backs. So, this commander's
name would have generated images of strength,
vitality, and an unstoppable force, and
by all accounts, it would be a good fit.
Although the elephant general Gajah Mada would
eventually rise through the new kingdom of
Majapahit to become one of its most influential
statesmen, his birth was relatively unexceptional.
We know little about his early life, but
he was likely born into a poor family in
the area around the city of Majapahit, and his
father was possibly killed in the war with the
Mongols. But he would prove his worth and
become the head of the king's elite royal
bodyguard, the Bhayangkara. After successfully
protecting the king through the Kuti rebellion,
Gajah Mada would be rewarded with the
governorship of a small province. Finally,
he would be named mahapatih,
or the right hand of the king.
The epic poem the Deshawarnana describes this
warrior statesman in the following terms.
Gajah Mada is the excellent party
of Majapahit, an officer valiant,
discerning in tactics, with a firm foundation
in loyalty and devotion to the king,
eloquent and skilled in speech, polite
and patient, constantly exerting himself,
unremitting; he watches over the king's
position as supreme ruler of the world.
King Jayanegara was clearly a man ill-suited
to rule, but with Gajah Mada's help,
he was able to keep hold of his kingdom
by his fingernails, and it's in the last
decade of his reign that a visitor from a
far-off land arrived on the shores of Java.
He was a traveller from the
northern Italian region of Friulia,
then a territory of the Holy Roman Empire,
and his name was Odoric of Pordenone.
Around the year 1318, Odoric had departed
from Venice and spent the next decade or
so traveling all over Asia, passing
through Persia, and seeing the ruins
of the ancient city of Persepolis. He then
sailed through the Strait of Hormuz to India,
and from there through the Straits of
Malacca to Borneo, Sumatra, and Java.
When he returned home, he dictated the memoirs
of his travels in a work entitled the Relatio
de Mirabilibus Orientalium Tatarorum, or
the Account of the Marvels of the Eastern
Tatars. In this text he provides a remarkable
snapshot of life in Java around the year 1320.
There is an island which is called Java, which is
a good 3,000 miles around. The king of this island
has under him seven crowned kings as vassals.
This island is very populous and is the second
best of all islands that be on the Earth. One
finds there cloves, pepper, nutmegs, and many
other precious spices that they grind there,
and all manner of necessities in great quantity.
Odoric was particularly impressed
by the royal palace of Jayanegara,
which was richly decorated in gold
mined from the volcanic mountain ranges.
The king of this island lives in a marvellous
and very large palace. Its steps are of gold
and silver alternately. The paving tiles
are likewise one gold and the next silver.
The walls are covered with plates of gold,
and there are mounted men sculpted out of
gold on them with golden circles around
their heads like the diadems we make for
the figures of saints, and these circles are
full of precious stones. To put it briefly,
this is the richest and loveliest
palace that there be in the whole world.
Odoric also records that many still remembered
the war with the Mongol Yuan Dynasty of China,
now nearly thirty years in the past.
The Great Khan of Cathay, who is the sovereign
emperor of all the Tatars, has often made war
with this king and often brought battle to
him, but this king has always defeated him.
But despite the glowing report
of Odoric and the ongoing help
of the elephant general Gajah Mada,
Jayanegara's reign was a poor one.
He was so insecure in his rule that he at one
point seems to have considered marrying two of his
own sisters, named Dyah Wiyat and Dyah Gitarja,
to ensure that no rivals could arise from the
royal line. When opposition to this plan exploded
in the court and their mother loudly protested,
King Jayanegara gave up on this idea, but he still
forbade his sisters from marrying anyone else.
King Jayanegara had two sisters
born of the same mother.
He did not permit them to be married to others,
wishing to keep them for himself. Therefore,
no prince dared remain openly at Majapahit.
Any man who appeared was driven away,
lest he seek their hands, and the other
nobles kept themselves hidden in fear.
Jayanegara confined these two princesses for
years in the women's quarters of the palace,
and prevented anyone from seeing
them. It was a microcosm of a rule
that seems to have been at every turn
paranoid, petty, and authoritarian.
Over the course of his reign, the kingdom of
Majapahit would falter. The island of Bali,
just a short hop over the Sunda Strait,
slipped out of his control around this time,
and people must have feared that the
whole kingdom would now disintegrate
and the land would return to destructive
civil war. But that was not to be the case.
That's because of a woman who had made
her name standing up to King Jayanegara,
the mother of the two imprisoned
princesses, a woman named Dyah Gayatri.
Dyah was a title that in old Javanese was given
to princes and princesses of the royal line,
and Dyah Gayatri had been the youngest daughter
of King Kertanegara, the last king of Singhasari.
She had also been the most senior wife of
the founder of Majapahit, Raden Wijaya,
and all her life she had been a quiet force
behind the lives of these great men. As a girl,
she had watched her father brand the face of the
Mongol envoys, and then saw her home of Singhasari
destroyed by the rebellion of Jaya-Katong. She had
fled through the rice fields to safety while her
home burned behind her. As a young woman, she
had watched the war with the Mongols unfold,
then seen her husband found the kingdom of
Majapahit, which now stood as his lasting
legacy. By now she was a widow in her fifties, and
had retired to become a Buddhist nun in a forest
monastery on the slope of a nearby mountain. But
she was still known by the title Rajapatni, a word
which means wife of kings , and which gave her the
prestige of a royal matriarch. The bumbling king
Jayanegara was her late husband's son by another
less senior wife, and we can only imagine how Dyah
Gayatri felt now watching from her monastery as he
veered the empire from crisis to crisis and kept
her two daughters under lock and key. She must
have feared that the legacy that she and Raden
Wijaya had built was about to be destroyed,
but she refused to let that happen. To help
her free her daughters, reclaim the kingdom, and
put it back on course, this royal matriarch would
enlist the help of the man who had recently been
rising in prominence in the kingdom of Majapahit,
the raging elephant who had become indispensable
to the feckless king, the soldier and statesman
who went by the name Gajah Mada. In the
year 1328, it seems they took their chance.
According to the official story related
in the royal chronicle the Pararaton,
that year King Jayanegara was suffering
from an unpleasant condition, a painful
boil or swelling of some kind, and when
he summoned his doctor, a man named Tanca,
he apparently forgot that he had previously
insulted or taken advantage of this man's wife.
Enraged at this, the doctor took his
revenge, as the Pararaton records.
Tanca's wife spread word that the king
had treated her dishonorably. Tanca was
summoned before Gajah Mada. At that time, King
Jayanegara was suffering from a swelling, and
could not leave his chambers. Tanca was ordered
to perform an operation with a sharp lancet,
and he approached beside the royal bed. Tanca
stabbed the king's boil once, then again with
the blade. But the weapon would not burst it,
for the king wore an amulet of protection.
Then the king was asked to set this
aside. He took off the charm and laid
it beside the bed. Tanca stabbed him again,
and this time the blade burst the boil. But
Tanca continued stabbing him and he did not
stop until the king died there upon the bed.
The doctor-turned-assassin, Tanca, was
swiftly killed by Gajah Mada, which meant,
perhaps conveniently, that his side of the
story could never be told. As historians,
we can never actually know what happened in
that room. But the slightly fanciful story
involving a magical amulet and a vengeful
doctor has left many historians wondering
if the true story wasn't a simpler one, that
Gajah Mada and the dowager queen Dyah Gayatri
had simply plotted together to kill
the king, framing the poor doctor.
Whether they had planned the whole thing or
just seized the opportunity on a stroke of good
luck, Gajah Mada and the dowager matriarch Dyah
Gayatri went on to seize control of the kingdom,
and it seems King Jayanegara was sufficiently
disliked that few people were all that concerned
about what might actually have happened
to him. But the royal matriarch and the
general prime minister faced a problem. Gajah
Mada himself had risen from humble beginnings,
and as a commoner, he had absolutely no
legitimacy to rule under Javanese law.
And while Dyah Gayatri was officially the next in
line to the throne, she had already taken a vow to
become a Buddhist nun, a position that prevented
her from holding any positions of earthly power,
and she had no sons who might take the throne.
In fact, the histories record that she had only
given birth to her two daughters, who were
now allowed to leave the palace for the first
time in years. The Deshawarnana describes
these women in conventionally poetic terms.
And then the king, Jayanegara, was left behind
as king of Majapahit with his princesses,
his youngest sisters, who were the
daughters of the worthy Rajapatni
the incomparable. They were both of the
greatest beauty, surpassing the women of
heaven. The elder was princess of Jiwana,
and the younger ruled as princess of Daha.
The Rajapatni Dyah Gayatri soon
appointed her young daughter,
Dyah Gitarja, to rule as queen in her place.
Verily in the shaka-year Moon Arrows Two Form,
the princess of Jiwana succeeded
in Majapahit as queen. It was the
disposition of the great Rajapatni that she
should be the auspicious leader of the world,
distinguished from others. It was she who made
her ruler and watched over all her affairs.
The princess soon took to the throne, and with
her mother watching over her, she would be a
far more capable ruler than her feckless brother.
She would take a royal name that meant the exalted
goddess of the three worlds, who the glory of
Vishnu radiates ; Tribhuwana Wijayatungadewi.
Tribhuwana was her mother's daughter. She
was a natural stateswoman, and was able
to stabilize the kingdom after the period
of poor leadership that had preceded her,
and she seems to have learned from the mistakes of
both her father and brother. Early in her reign,
she faced a rebellion by two men named Sadeng and
Keta, and a conflict arose in her court over which
of her generals would lead her army into battle.
These kinds of political disputes had plagued the
last two kings, but Tribhuwana resolved it
in a simple way. Rather than show favor to
one general over the other, she simply led the
army herself, as the Deshawarnana describes.
In shaka-year Fires Arrows Suns, their enemies
were destroyed. Sadeng and Keta were defeated,
overcome by her personal retinue. Further
in the shaka-year Arrows Seasons Eyes Navel,
the king of Bali was evil and
base. He was attacked with an army,
broken and completely crushed. Every kind of
evildoer was fearful, and made off quickly.
Tribhuwana's early successes on the
battlefield gave her a taste for conquest,
and over her rule, this queen of Java would
embark on a massive expansion of Majapahit,
to spread its influence all over the archipelago.
To embark on this mission, she appointed as her
mahapatih, or prime minister, the general who
had done more than perhaps anyone else to keep
the young kingdom together, and who had worked
with her mother to depose the previous king. This
was the rampaging elephant himself, Gajah Mada.
By all accounts, Gajah Mada rose to this
challenge. Spurred on by his warlike queen,
the Pararaton records him swearing a remarkable
oath of conquest before the entire royal court.
Gajah Mada swore, "Until I have conquered the
entire Nusantara archipelago, I will eat no
spices nor take any rest. If I have conquered
the Gorom Islands and the island of Seram,
the kingdom of Tanjung-Pura, the kingdoms
of Haru and Pahang, the Dompu regency,
the island of Bali, the lands of Sunda, along
with the Tumasik and Palembang of Sumatra,
then and only then will I
eat spices and take my rest.
Over the next three decades, Gajah Mada would
lead the armies of Majapahit across the seas,
and would bring ever more lands under the
influence and control of the empire. The
Italian traveller Ludovico di Varthema
describes the weapons of the Javanese
that he saw when he visited sometime
later around 1505. They carry bows,
and the greater part darts of cane. Some also use
blowpipes, with which they throw poison darts,
and they throw them with the mouth, and however
little they draw blood, the wounded person dies.
The 12th-century Javanese poem, the Bhomantaka,
describes an idealized army marching to battle,
and gives a sense for what it would
have been like to see the forces
of Gajah Mada landing on the shores of
each island in turn and preparing for war.
Their weapons were spears and lances, and there
were also thousands of bows. Then came the riding
elephants, and their weapons were spears, lances,
javelins, and clubs. Many heroes were mounted on
horses, skilled riders in horseback combat. The
spears and very sharp knives, when whirled, glowed
brightly. Men came bearing lances and shields,
and others with slingshots. Their casings shone,
wrapped in silk and gilded, and their various
jackets were like clouds traveling over the earth.
The Majapahit forces of Queen Tribhuwana
Wijayatungadewi crossed the sea to the east
and reconquered the small island of Bali
in 1343. After that, they went northwest
and absorbed most of the coastal regions of the
larger island of Sumatra into her growing empire.
Other kingdoms were incorporated peacefully
into the empire as tributary subjects,
such as the large island of Sulawesi,
whose name means iron island on account
of the high quality iron it produced
and exported around the region.
The later poem, the Deshawarnana, lists
at length all of the island territories
that were either conquered by Majapahit or
agreed to pay it tribute without a fight.
The islands and lesser islands in the
first place coming under the territory
of the Malay islands are Jambi and Palembang,
Keritang, Teba, and Dharmasraya. Follow Kandis,
Kahwas, Manangkabwa, Siyak, Rekan, Kampar and
Pane, Kampe, Haru and Mandahiling, Tumihang,
Parlak and Barat, Lewas and Samudra, as well
as Lamuri, Batan, Lampung, and Barus. Those
are the main ones among the Malay islands.
All these countries are subject and obedient.
The great queen Tribhuwana Wijayatungadewi
would rule for twenty-two years,
and her reign saw the rise of Majapahit to a
true thalassocracy, or an empire of the sea.
But she must have known that
her reign couldn't last forever.
In 1350, her mother, the great royal matriarch
Dyah Gayatri, died, most likely in her forest
monastery after a long and accomplished life. Her
daughter Tribhuwana had been ruling ostensibly on
behalf of her mother, and it seems that once the
old woman died, her situation would also become
untenable. But luckily by this time she had had
a son, who was now the first in the royal line,
and he had just come of age at sixteen
years old. His name was Hayam Wuruk.
When this young prince Hayam
Wuruk came to the throne,
he would have been crowned with enormous
ceremony and celebration. The historian
Herald Van Der Linde describes the rituals
associated with a Javanese coronation.
At sunset on the eve of the first day of the
first month of the year, priests entered the inner
pavilion of the royal palace, followed by acolytes
chanting sacred Sanskrit texts. King Hayam Wuruk
sat on a throne in the amazing pavilion, where
matted-haired rishi hermits and religious leaders
sprinkled holy water over him to wash away the
evils of the past. As darkness descended, oil
lamps were lit around the palace, a spectacular
sight. At the striking of a gong, Gajah Mada
led the senior ministers to a large pavilion in
front of the palace gates before a growing crowd.
Hayam Wuruk was a multi-talented king. He was
apparently an accomplished singer and dancer, and
a lover of shadow puppet plays. The poet of the
Deshawarnana describes the auspicious omens that
took place upon the birth of this prince, as the
island's great volcanoes rumbled their approval.
At his birth in the shaka-year Seasons Arrow
Suns, the prince was already destined to be king.
The signs of his miraculous and extraordinary
nature were that the Earth quaked and rumbled.
There was a rain of ash. Thunder and lightning
zigzagged through the sky. Mount Kampud erupted,
and the wretched evildoers around it were
annihilated and died without a gasp. Such is the
nature of his reign that the whole of the land of
Java has been humbled and bows down in submission.
Like her mother before her, Tribhuwana
did not completely vanish from political
life when she stepped away from her
throne. Throughout the rest of her life,
she would act as a counsellor and
advisor for her son, and together
they would usher in what is widely regarded
as the golden age of the empire of Majapahit.
When Hayam Wuruk came to the throne, he
inherited a capital city of no little
magnificence. Over the preceding decades, it
had been the site of constant construction,
and now bloomed with palaces and temples complete
with pillared audience halls and pavilions.
In this era, all roads led to Majapahit,
and its status as a crossroads of Java
wasn't just a metaphor. The epic poem
Deshawarnana describes the royal palace.
Let us describe the layout of the
awe-inspiring royal palace. Its
wall is of red brick. It goes right around
and is thick and high. On the western side,
the palace mouth faces onto the great square in
the midst of deep encircling with buddhi trees in
rows and neatly shaped, all thick with
festoons. On the north is the ceremonial gate,
splendid and extraordinary, its doors of
iron adorned with countless designs. To the
south of this is the crossroads,
otherworldly in its elegance.
From these crossroads, great highways snaked
off into the country in all directions.
It was part of the usual ceremony of kingship
that the king of Majapahit would routinely make
journeys around the whole of Java, meeting his
citizens, and seeing the sights of the land,
visiting villages, holy shrines, and reminding
vassal kingdoms about who was in charge.
It was on one of these journeys that King
Hayam Wuruk brought his court poet, a man
named Prapanca, who would go on to be the author
of the poem Deshawarnana. Prapanca speaks of the
honor in his poem, describing himself in the third
person. In the shaka-year Moon Snake Sun, in the
month of Bhadra-pada, at the fullness of the moon,
King Hayam Wuruk went on a journey to Lamajang to
take note of all there was to see. All the princes
of Java with their wives again went with the king,
with servants and vehicles, officials
and officers from the whole of Majapahit,
and in particular the king's priests and court
poets accompanied him. So this man by the pen
name of Prapanca joined in the pursuit of
beauty, attending at the feet of the king.
According to his own account, Prapanca seems
to have embarked on writing the Deshawarnana
because he felt unable to write the kind of poetry
that the more senior court poets were producing,
usually heroic epics about the Hindu gods,
as he describes in the following extract.
His motive was, after all, to follow the king
wherever he went in the hope of being favored.
But he still does not know how to
achieve poetic effects, and is most
unlikely to succeed in composing a song on the
writing tablet. And this is the reason why he
describes all the places passed through and
sets out their names in order along the road.
Ironically, the Deshawarnana is today one of the
most famous pieces of literature to survive from
the Javanese golden era, and it is by far the
most useful to historians. Today, the poem is a
remarkable source that captures a snapshot of life
on Java during the reign of Hayam Wuruk. And for
all of this, we have the poet Prapanca's apparent
inferiority complex to thank. Along their journey,
Prapanca watched the king carefully and noted
down the beauty of the land they passed through.
At Dampar and at Patun-jungan, the king relaxed
and made his way along the beach. To the east,
his path followed the level sands, which was
so firm that the carriages could drive over
them. He made a halt on the banks of a lake
thick with white and red lotuses in flower,
and was absorbed in watching the giant
shrimps moving about in the limpid water,
clearly visible in the depths. But the
royal journey wasn't always an easy one.
In his text, we get a sense for the
challenges of moving over land during
the rainy season. The road, just at the
point where it runs northward from the sea,
over its whole length was rough and narrow. On
top of this, it rained, so that the steep places
became slippery, and some of the carriages
came loose and collided with each other.
Due to these challenges, travel by road
was largely only possible during the dry
season. For the rest of the year,
goods were transported by river,
taking rice and other export crops downstream
to the great port cities on barges. These boats
would then sail back up the rivers with luxury
goods imported from China, India, and elsewhere.
These port cities were the beating heart of
the Majapahit Empire, and the large numbers
of Chinese coins found in their archaeological
sites testify to the booming trade that went on.
At each of these ports, the sails of
hundreds of ships would be visible,
coming and going with countless trade goods. And
among these, the most lucrative were the spices
grown on the islands of the archipelago
that were prized all around the world,
such as pepper, cardamom, and ginger. But
the rarest of all were cloves and nutmeg.
Cloves and nutmeg were brought to Majapahit on
large ships that sailed from a small group of
islands which are called the islands of Malaku,
and would come to be known as the Spice Islands.
While cloves were grown all over these islands,
nutmeg was extremely limited in cultivation,
occurring only on ten islands in the tiny
archipelago of Banda. Wild nutmeg had long
been harvested by the peoples native to the Banda
Islands, but it was a particularly difficult plant
to cultivate. Nutmeg seeds will fail to germinate
if they aren't planted in soil within a week,
making them difficult to transport by sea,
and the particular environment of volcanic
soil that they evolved in means that they are
fragile and difficult to nurture to full size.
As a result of these difficulties, the
Banda islanders claimed that nutmeg was
simply a gift of the gods and could not
be cultivated by human hands. Instead,
they would travel to the parts of the forest
where it grew wild to collect its prized seeds,
and they kept the location of these
groves a carefully guarded secret.
But despite its extreme rarity, the fragrant
nutmeg seeds that these islanders harvested
traveled all around the world. The spice
would reach Constantinople in the 6th century,
and instantly became a sought-after
commodity and mark of luxury.
Nutmeg would even be mentioned as a spice to
flavor English ale in Chaucer's Canterbury Tales,
which was written during the time of the
Majapahit Empire. At times nutmeg would
sell on the other side of the world for
more than an equivalent weight of gold.
As a result of this global trade, the
rulers of the Banda Islands would come
to be known around the region as
the orang kaya , or rich men , and
the entirety of this trade passed
through the major ports of Majapahit.
To transport these goods across the seas and
oceans, the sailors of Majapahit voyaged in
large vessels known as djongs. These
were the descendants of the Borobudur
ships that had sailed to Madagascar and
Eastern Africa in the preceding centuries,
and by this time, some of these ships had
reportedly grown to phenomenal proportions.
Reports on the true size of these vessels vary,
but some sources record djongs that reached a
size of 80 meters long. They were built with
layered hulls that made them exceptionally strong,
and were able to transport a thousand soldiers
and more than a thousand tons of cargo.
The sight of these massive djongs astonished
European explorers when they arrived in the
archipelago in the 16th century. One Portuguese
admiral and explorer, Alfonso de Albuquerque,
wrote about encountering one of
these enormous vessels in 1511.
The whole fleet went back along the coast
in the same order as they had first come,
and when they were in the latitude of
the Powder Island, they sighted two very
large junks and gave chase to them.
One of these, which was from India,
surrendered immediately, but
the other junk would not do so.
The Portuguese gave chase to the massive Javanese
ship and made several attempts to board it,
but these were all unsuccessful. The Europeans
even opened fire on the djong with their cannons,
but found that the three or four layers of wood
with which the Javanese built their ships simply
absorbed the cannon fire, and the vast vessel
sailed on. In a letter written sometime later,
one of the Portuguese captains, Fernao Pires de
Andrade, describes the massive Javanese ship.
The junk was the largest seen by men of
these parts so far. It carried a thousand
fighting men on board, and your lordship can
believe me that it was an amazing thing to see,
because beside it, our own vessel, the
Anunciada, did not look like a ship at
all. We attacked it with bombards, but
even the shots of the largest cannon did
not pierce it below the waterline. It was so
monstrous that no man had ever seen the like.
Eventually, the smaller and more maneuverable
Portuguese ships were able to disable the larger
djong by breaking its two massive rudders. This
finally brought the men on board to surrender.
The Europeans were so impressed with the size
of these Javanese djongs that they sailed one
of them all the way back home, where it was used
for a time as a warship in the fleet guarding
the Gibraltar Strait. Although we have little
reliable data on when the ships of the Javanese
reached such a massive scale, it is reasonable
to assume that they were at least approaching
that size during the reign of Hayam Wuruk,
when the power of Majapahit was at its peak.
These enormous ships would have been the
crucial backbone of the Majapahit Empire,
with their enormous capacity for cargo and their
ability to transport thousands of men, horses,
and even elephants from island to island
wherever they were needed. And of course,
they would have made a powerful statement about
the power and prestige of the empire of Majapahit.
By now, the Majapahit sphere of influence
stretched over the sea for thousands of
kilometers, and they had monopolized the
lucrative spice routes from the Malaku
Islands so that their wealth would have swelled to
previously unimagined heights. Over this period,
Majapahit began to take on the form of
what has been called a mandala empire.
In Sanskrit, the word mandala means circle , and
it has come to describe a style of traditional
geometric pattern used to represent a kind of
map of the universe. Reflected in the shapes
of the Buddhist temples at Sewu and Borobudur,
these are designed to help an adherent achieve
a state of meditation. Although the forms of
these mandalas differ, many show the sacred
mountain Meru at the center of the world,
sometimes surrounded by the world ocean.
Around this is a square palace with four gates,
and then a circle representing the continents
outside it, the heavens and the world of the
gods forming the outside of the pattern. The
mandala presents the vision of a world ordered in
a strict hierarchy radiating out from the center,
and so, it's no surprise it has long been
used as a way of visualizing royal power.
As early as the 4th century BC, the Indian
writer Kautilya, in his work the Arthshastra,
described what he called the Raja Mandala, or
Mandala of Kings, in which a powerful ruler
will bring other less powerful ones under his
control. This idea has become popular among modern
historians seeking to understand how Southeast
Asian states of this time were organized,
and as some evidence that this is also how
the Javanese of the time would have thought
of their world. The epic poem the Deshawarnana
describes the structure of the Majapahit Empire
like the solar system, with power radiating
out from the center like the rays of the sun.
The royal compound at Majapahit the incomparable
is as sun and the moon, and the courtyards of
the many quarters, each with its own particular
charm, are rays of light in relation to it. Like
the stars and planets are the various remaining
cities, Daha the foremost, and the other islands
and all the surrounding countries which seek
refuge and in numbers come into the presence.
It's still an open question exactly how much power
Majapahit exerted over its vassal states. Some
empires like the Roman Empire ruled with direct
control. When they conquered a new area, they
erased previous forms of government and social
structures, and imposed their own on absorbed
territories. But we don't see much evidence
of that in the case of Majapahit. Subordinate
kings and rulers on the outer islands certainly
paid symbolic homage to the king in Majapahit.
They likely provided an agreed upon tribute each
year and a certain number of soldiers and ships
for any military action undertaken by the empire.
But beyond that, it's likely that the lords of
each island and tributary kingdom continued to
exert more or less total control over their own
affairs. This arrangement suited everyone well.
Cultural identities on each individual island
were relatively distinct and deeply entrenched.
Local languages and customs were different on each
island, and few people around the region wanted
to be directly ruled by a Javanese governor,
or to have Javanese troops stationed in
their hometowns. And for the Majapahit,
appointing governors and stationing troops to
put down rebellions and uprisings would have
been an unwelcome expense. The mandala
structure was cheap and efficient.
While times were good and the empire was
strong, it ensured a maximum level of
compliance and cooperation from subjects with the
lightest possible touch, and allowed everyone to
profit from the great traffic of trade that
flowed along the great arteries of the sea.
From the center of the mandala in Majapahit,
fleets of djong ships sailed back and forth
among the islands, bringing trade and tribute
back to its booming ports. But as with any empire,
sometimes its subjects had to be kept
in line, as the Deshawarnana describes.
The other countries, all that were under the
care of Java, obeyed the king's commands,
and each was true in what it did. Furthermore,
any that transgressed his commands was attacked
and wiped out completely by the squadrons
of the various valiant naval officers.
One such example occurred in the year 1375,
when one of the subject kings of the empire
seemed to get ideas above his station.
The troublesome king in question was a man
named Adityawarman, who had been put in power
by Majapahit on the large island of Sumatra, a
short hop over the sea from Java. Adityawarman
was something of a narcissist. He was fond
of commissioning massive statues of himself
larger than any that have been uncovered of other
kings in the region, and over the preceding years,
he had begun to act in an insubordinate manner.
At one point he had a stone tablet inscribed that
showed a list of kings, and he had the insolence
to place his own name above King Hayam Wuruk s.
This all would have caused rumbles of
consternation at the court of Majapahit.
But Adityawarman would go too far when he sent his
own envoys to the court of the emperor of China,
bypassing his king completely. One
Javanese epic poem, the Brata-Yuda,
describes the rage of the demon king Ravana upon
getting news of the death of his sons. But we
might imagine it a fitting description of Hayam
Wuruk's reaction when he heard that Adityawarman
had been going over his head and making overtures
to China without consulting him. The monarch was
furiously enraged. He gnawed his moustaches, his
countenance was inflamed, and his bosom red as the
wawawari flower. Sweat exuded from every pore.
The angles of his mouth trembled. His eyelashes
stuck together. He vaunted. He called aloud. He
challenged all his enemies to meet him at once.
Hayam Wuruk summoned the Chinese ambassador to
Sumatra, and after lambasting him, apparently
had the man beheaded and his head sent back to
China in a bag. In perhaps a sign of the power of
Majapahit at this time, the Chinese didn't respond
in kind. Instead, they bashfully apologized for
their mistake, and would eventually send a gift
of fine fabrics and a batch of paper money to
the Javanese court to make amends. But from the
vain king Adityawarman, no apology would suffice.
King Hayam Wuruk amassed his army, as many as
300 warships, and according to the chronicles,
200,000 soldiers to crush this upstart king.
And although we don't hear what happens to him,
Adityawarman never appears in any other
written records or inscriptions again.
Now Hayam Wuruk was on the war path. After
crushing Adityawarman, the Majapahit fleet
rounded on another problematic vassal. This
man ruled the walled settlement of Singapura,
now the modern city of Singapore, and his name
was Parameswara. After a month-long siege,
the Majapahit forces broke through the walls
and slaughtered the inhabitants. To this day,
legend has it that the iron-rich reddish clay
soil of Singapore was stained that color by the
blood spilled during this massacre. Parameswara,
the king of Singapura, fled north to the area of
the Malacca Strait, but he would remain a thorn
in the side of Majapahit for some time to come.
The Adityawarman incident shows that the
empire of Majapahit was held together by
trade and diplomacy and the promise
of mutual peace and prosperity. But
it was also very much backed by the
threat of force. Over this period,
the royal capital would flourish. But this
golden age of Majapahit could not last forever,
and its end would come about after the
death of its last great king, Hayam Wuruk.
King Hayam Wuruk died likely in the year 1389,
and with him the light began to
leave the court of Majapahit.
The great statesman and general Gajah Mada had
died twenty-five years earlier, and Hayam Wuruk's
mother, Queen Tribhuwana Wijayatungadewi,
had also died a decade or so after that.
There now seems to have been something of
a vacuum of talent in the Majapahit court.
Exacerbating the problem was the complexity of
Javanese succession laws, which had developed to
deal with the fact that kings of this time always
had multiple wives. In ideal circumstances, the
law would unambiguously favor one successor over
another, and there would be no confusion about who
would take the throne. But fate had dealt Hayam
Wuruk a bad hand when it came to his succession.
He had failed to have a son by his principal wife,
and so his closest legal heir was
therefore a woman named Kusumawardhani,
his daughter by a lower-ranking wife. She
had married a man named Wikramawardhana,
and so it seemed likely that he would become king
despite having only married into the royal family.
The Deshawarnana describes this couple in
glowing terms. They have as daughter Princess
Kusumawardhani, a blameless young princess who's
paid homage in the royal compound of Kabalan and
is of the utmost charm. Prince Wikramawardhana
will be her proper match, as everyone says they
will be like a god and goddess when they marry
later, bringing happiness to people's hearts.
But Hayam Wuruk did also have a son by a
secondary, less-senior wife. In the histories,
he is known only by the title Bhre Wirabhumi,
or the lord of a place called Wirabhumi. Being a
man and the direct descendant of Hayam Wuruk also
gave him a strong claim to the throne despite his
mother being of a lower rank than Kusumawardhani
s, and this situation of two people having a
comparable claim was a recipe for disaster. Hayam
Wuruk seems to have sensed the danger while he was
still alive. In an attempt to remedy the situation
and cool off the rivalry between these two men,
he divided the empire into the Western Court, the
capital of Majapahit, and the Eastern Court, where
the lord of Wirabhumi held sway. The exact details
of this arrangement are unknown, but it was a
clear and obvious rift now splitting the kingdom's
Javanese heartlands in two. The situation seems to
have gotten so bad that at one point, the Chinese
chronicle, the Ming Shilu, notes that the two
different courts were each sending their envoys to
meet independently with the emperor's ambassadors.
Like the rumblings and earthquakes before
a great eruption, the signs of trouble must
have been obvious to anyone who was paying
attention, and in the years that followed,
the rift would tear apart the land
of Java and the empire it ruled.
The name for the conflict that follows is
found in the chronicle of the Pararaton.
There it is called the Regreg, a word that in
Javanese means bit by bit , and can be used
to describe something falling apart piece by
piece. As we will see, this was a fitting name,
as the conflict would bring about the steady
coming apart of the mandala empire of Majapahit
that had held together over the last century. The
Pararaton describes the conflict that unfolded.
They came to blows. There was division, and
men died in the division. After three years,
there then arose again the Regreg War.
Both sides prepared themselves. All the
lords asked themselves, "Whom shall
I follow?" Then the fighting began.
The Regreg War would rage for two years, and
over this time, neither side could gain the
upper hand. The Pararaton describes the
back and forth nature of the fighting.
First the Western palace was defeated. Their
lords were hard pressed. In distress they wished
to flee. Then they said, "Do not flee yet. Let us
fight them." Then the Eastern palace was defeated.
The strength of the mandala empire
system was in how light a hold it
exerted on its vassals. It was a cheap and
efficient way to run an imperial system,
but this strength in times of stability
became a weakness when times got hard.
For the kings who swore allegiance to Majapahit,
it was all too easy when the empire was distracted
to simply turn away and quietly stop
paying its fees or sending it troops.
With the power of Majapahit's fleet and army now
focused entirely on the war between its Western
and Eastern courts, many of its formerly most
loyal subjects simply slipped out of its grasp.
One of these subjects was in the region
of Malayu, which during the Regreg War,
drifted under the sovereignty of the powerful
kingdom of Ayutthaya in what is now Thailand.
On the island of Sumatra, a Chinese pirate named
Chen Zuyi from Guangdong even took advantage
of the chaos caused by the Regreg War to seize
control of the wealthy port city of Palembang.
This man would run Palembang as a pirate
fortress for the better part of a decade,
using it as a base to raid the wealthy shipping
that passed through the Malacca Strait, and
using forged bronze seals to create counterfeit
licenses and aid smuggling into and out of China.
The Chinese-Muslim writer Ma Huan
wrote about the situation in his work,
A Survey of the Ocean Shores.
Chen Zuyi plundered ships and prayed on both
native and foreign merchants for several years.
On the northern coast of Borneo, the Brunei
Kingdom had also begun to ignore the overlordship
of Majapahit, and by 1405, Western Borneo had
also drifted away. These small kingdoms would
instead seek protection under the influence of
another power that was now flexing its muscles
with increasing confidence on the waves.
That was the rising Ming Dynasty of China.
By this time, the Mongol Yuan Dynasty had
collapsed, and the Mongols had been forcibly
thrown out of China. Now, a new dynasty
known as the Ming had taken its place.
The Ming ruled over a devastated
land that had suffered immensely
over the years of Mongol conquest
and misrule by the Yuan emperors,
exacerbated by the ravages of the Black
Death. But now, China was rebuilding.
Ultimately, the Ming Dynasty has been remembered
as a paranoid and inward-looking state,
which virtually bankrupted itself with the
construction of its vast Great Wall in the north,
sealing itself off from the world.
But at the start of the 15th century,
Ming China looked quite different.
This was partly due to the reign
of an ambitious and outward-looking
ruler known as the Yongle Emperor.
The Yongle Emperor was a patron of learning, and
sponsored the writing of a great encyclopedia
made up of 23,000 written scrolls in an
attempt to record all the world's knowledge.
He was fascinated by everything, and
especially the world outside of China,
as he recorded in his work Ming Taizong Baoxun,
or the Valuable Teachings of Emperor Yongle.
Whenever I can find the time, I read history
books and the classics so as to avoid
idol living. I constantly remind myself that
the world is so vast and state affairs so
important that I cannot succumb to
laziness and complacency for even a
moment. Once one has succumbed to laziness and
complacency, everything will become stagnant.
As a result of this fascination with the outer
world, throughout his reign, he sent out a flurry
of diplomatic missions to all corners of Asia,
letting everyone know that China was once again
open for business. And as part of this effort,
he ordered the construction of a grand fleet
designed to sail around the region and remind
the people of every land of the might of China.
To build his fleet, the Yongle Emperor ordered
the construction of a vast shipyard at a place
called Longjiang, or Dragon River. This
sprawling industrial complex was built at
the point where the Yangtze River is met by the
smaller Qinhuai in the Ming capital of Nanjing.
And it would be the largest shipyard anywhere
in the world. On its seven long, large docks,
at least 100 ships could be built at any one time.
To help in his mammoth effort, the Yongle Emperor
invited more than 20,000 craftsmen to work here on
his ships, and timbers of elm, cedar, and camphor
were brought in enormous quantities to the city
of Nanjing, transported from inland ports down the
rivers on flat-bottomed barges. The noise of the
shipwrights shouting and calling, the thump of the
massive beams being lifted into place, the beating
of chisels and hammers on nails, all of this would
have sounded over the rooftops of Nanjing in
the early years of the 15th century. For China,
it was the sound of industry and progress, but
for the power of Majapahit far across the sea
in the south, it might as well have been the
sound of nails being driven into its coffin.
By the year 1405, as the Regreg
civil war dragged on in Majapahit,
the Yongle Emperor had completed his
grand fleet, and now all he needed was
an admiral to lead it. The man he chose
was a eunuch, a giant named Zheng He.
In some ways, Zheng He was an unlikely
candidate to become China's most famous
sailor and admiral. For one thing,
he had barely any sailing experience,
but he had spent much of his life serving
the Yongle Emperor as a military commander,
and had proved himself a capable and loyal
general. Zheng He was a Muslim born into a devout
family in the southwest of China, but he had been
captured during the wars of the preceding decades,
and had been castrated and brought up
a eunuch as a kind of military slave.
One writer named Yuan Zhongche describes his
towering stature with perhaps some exaggeration.
He was seven feet tall and had a waist
about five feet in circumference. His
cheeks and forehead were high, but his
nose was small. He had glaring eyes,
teeth as white and well-shaped
as shells, and a voice as loud
as a huge bell. He knew a great deal about
warfare, and was well accustomed to battle.
On the 11th of July 1405, under the command
of Admiral Zheng He, this vast fleet set sail,
and it would have made an awe-inspiring site.
It comprised a total of 317 vessels of
the latest design, including at least 60
vast treasure ships that were among the
largest in the world. By some sources,
these could have measured more than 120 meters
in length and 50 in breadth, making them still
among the largest wooden sailing ships built
anywhere in the world. These vessels were each
fitted with twenty-four cast bronze cannons, and
were beautifully decorated, too, with their prows
carved with animal heads, dragons, phoenixes,
and eagles, all painted in bright colors
Like the ancient Greeks, Egyptians, Phoenicians,
and Romans, the Chinese painted eyes on the fronts
of their vessels so that the ships seemed to take
on a life of their own and see their way through
mists and stormy seas. On board these hundreds
of ships were a total of 28,000 men, including
sailors and soldiers, but also diplomats,
astronomers, linguists, interpreters, and doctors,
as well as carpenters and shipbuilders for if
the vessels needed repairing while at sea. On
one stone tablet that the admiral later erected
in Fujian, he describes this great voyage.
We have traversed more than 100,000 li of immense
water spaces, and have beheld in the ocean huge
waves like mountains rising sky high, and we
have set eyes on barbarian regions far away,
hidden in a blue transparency of light vapors,
while our sails, loftily unfurled like clouds day
and night, continued their course as rapidly
as a star traversing those savage waves.
Although outfitted with cannons, the treasure
ships were not primarily warships. They were
in fact vast cargo vessels, their holds
filled to the brim with Chinese silks,
cotton, tea, wine, oil, iron, and candles, along
with other luxuries, all intended for trade with
the strange lands they would encounter along the
way. From these lands they brought back spices,
gemstones, and even in the year 1414, a live
giraffe, which had been brought to Bengal by
some African delegates from Malindi. Impressed
at the sight of the treasure fleet, these men had
gifted one of these animals to the Chinese,
who brought it home to no little amazement.
The Yongle Emperor was no stranger
to receiving exotic animals as gifts,
and there was even a part of his palace
devoted to keeping and caring for them;
elephants and rhinoceroses from Champa, bears
from Siam, parrots and peacocks from Java, and
ostriches from Aden. But of all these, it was the
giraffe that he asked his court artists to paint.
Alongside the vast treasure ships sailed a
countless array of different support vessels,
some carrying horses and troops, others warships
for defense. Other boats were floating water
tankers, ensuring the thousands of personnel
wouldn't go thirsty on long voyages between ports.
The ships communicated between one another using
large flags, signal bells, a drum, and gongs,
along with ten lanterns that could signal at
night. They even carried carrier pigeons to
communicate over longer distances. The ultimate
destination of the treasure fleet was the city of
Kozhikode in the modern Indian state of Kerala,
but the fleet was ordered to stop at every large
port and kingdom on the way to demonstrate
the might of the Ming Emperor. It was in 1406
that the Ming fleet arrived in Java, while the
Regreg civil war was reaching its bloody height.
When the Chinese treasure fleet arrived in Java,
they might have expected to encounter the scenes
of wealth and prosperity that had been recorded
by previous visitors, but they would find instead
a troubled land devastated by civil war.
The treasure ships anchored off the coast,
and a group of Chinese soldiers and merchants
came ashore in Western Java hoping to trade.
But the Western king Wikramawardhana, the husband
of Hayam Wuruk's daughter, believed that his rival
in the east had brought the Chinese to intervene
in the civil war. While the Chinese visitors were
trading in the marketplace, King Wikramawardhana's
soldiers swept down on them from all sides.
The cries of the Javanese warriors and the
screams of the dying would have joined the
pops and bangs of cannons that would have
sounded all around the marketplace. The
acrid smell of gunpowder and blood would have
lingered on the air. When the smoke cleared,
170 Chinese merchants and sailors were dead,
and the rest had fled back to their ships.
Admiral Zheng He had enough soldiers with him
that he could have invaded Java in response,
and perhaps like the Mongols more
than a hundred years earlier,
he could have decisively tipped the balance
in this civil war. But he was a pragmatic man,
and he decided to tread a more considered path.
He treated his wounded on board the ships,
and sent envoys back to the Yongle Emperor asking
him what to do. In the time of Hayam Wuruk thirty
years earlier, China had steered clear of
conflict with the powerful Majapahit Empire,
sending money and goods in order to avoid a
war. But now Majapahit was weakened and divided.
This time it was King Wikramawardhana who would
send a groveling apology to the Chinese court,
and the Ming Shilu, or Records of the Ming
Dynasty, records what the emperor said in reply.
There is no doubt as to your guilt. You
acted on the basis of greed and anger,
and you have acted against heaven.
Is there anything more serious than this? Just
as I was about to raise an army to punish you,
I have seen that you are capable of repenting your
mistakes, and I have thus leniently stopped the
dispatch of troops. But what of the 170 people
who died innocently? You must immediately pay
60,000 liang of gold as compensation for
their lives and to atone for your crime.
A year later, a Javanese ship arrived in
China with only a sixth of the sum of gold
that the Chinese emperor had demanded, along
with a letter explaining that the bankrupt
kingdom could not afford to pay any more.
The Chinese emperor responded magnanimously.
What I want from those people
who live far away is that they
acknowledge their guilt. But I do not
want to enrich myself with their gold.
The point had been made, and
the humiliation of Majapahit
was total. Everyone in the region took notice.
In 1424, Chinese records show that
when one king in Sumatra died,
his son sent out a letter asking permission to
succeed him as king, and he sent it not to the
kings of Majapahit in Java, but to the Chinese
emperor in the Ming court. This shows just how
far the star of Majapahit had fallen, and
how the might of China was on the rise.
Although Admiral Zheng He had declined to fight
on this occasion, the treasure fleet was more than
capable of doing battle on the seas, and alongside
their main diplomatic and mercantile mission, its
admiral had been given some less peaceful tasks
to complete on their voyage. Chief among these
was a mission to destroy the pirate fortress that
still held out at the Sumatran port of Palembang,
which had risen up due to the weakness of the
Majapahit Empire. The Mingshi, or History of Ming,
describes how the pirate chief Chen Zuyi had been
playing a clever double game attempting to mollify
the Ming emperor. In the fourth year of the Yongle
reign, the pirate chieftain of the old port,
Chen Zuyi, sent his son to the Ming court.
However, although he sent tributes to the court,
he was plundering the seas, and thus obstructing
the comings and goings of the tributes envoys.
On its way home through the straits of Malacca,
the enormous treasure fleet took its chance.
They sailed along the mangrove-crusted
coast of Sumatra towards Palembang,
which the Chinese called the old port. We can
only imagine the sight that greeted the pirates
of Palembang as the hundreds of colorful
ships bore down on them on the horizon.
When they arrived at the port city, they
demanded the surrender of the pirate chief
Chen Zuyi. According to the Ming Shilu, or Records
of the Ming Dynasty, the pirate chief attempted to
use deception to gain the upper hand. When
he arrived at the old port of Palembang,
he came across Zuyi and others, and sent people
to bring them to negotiate their pacification.
Zuyi and the others feigned surrender, but
secretly plotted to attack the imperial army.
Zheng He and the others found out about this and,
marshalling the troops, prepared their defences.
The ensuing battle would be the first test
of the power of the Yongle Emperor's fleet.
The Ming ships would have rammed into the pirate
vessels, hurled gunpowder bombs from catapults,
and fired special kinds of fireworks filled
with scraps of paper designed to spread fire
and terror and ignite enemy sails. They would
have also sent volleys of flaming arrows flying
towards the pirate ships. The result was a
resounding victory for the Ming treasure fleet.
The pirate Zuyi suffered a great defeat.
Over 5,000 of the bandit gang were killed,
while ten of the bandit ships were burnt and
seven were captured. Further, two counterfeit
bronze seals were seized, and three prisoners,
including Zuyi, were taken alive. When they
arrived at the capital in chains, it was ordered
that all of the prisoners were to be beheaded.
With this pirate threat crushed,
the Ming Chinese quickly moved to
establish a governor of the area to
prevent a resurgence of any piracy.
The man they chose, a Muslim named Shi Jinching,
had once been an official of the Majapahit Empire.
The old port pacification superintendency
was established, and it was ordered that Shi
Jinching be appointed as the pacification
superintendent. A seal, a title patent,
headwear, and a belt, patterned fine silks,
and silk gauzes were conferred upon him.
While the rulers of Majapahit had their
backs turned, fighting amongst themselves,
the Ming Chinese had swept in and stamped
their seal of authority on the Malacca Strait.
To strengthen this grip over the narrow
and crucial waterway, the Chinese would
also bring under their wing the young city of
Malacca, which had recently been growing in
wealth and importance. Malacca was a hub
for another tide of change that was now
sweeping through the archipelago. That was
the steady spread of the religion of Islam.
Islam had long had a presence in the Indonesian
archipelago, and had arrived with traders who
traveled back and forth across the Indian
Ocean, bringing nutmeg and cloves to the
markets of Egypt and Arabia. But now this young
religion began to make advances in all directions.
The European traveller Marco Polo
remarked on the change already
underway on the island of Sumatra when he
passed through the town of Perlak in 1292.
The people of Perlak used to be idolaters,
but owing to contact with Saracen merchants,
who continually resort here in their ships, they
have all been converted to the law of Mohammed.
Part of the reason for the spread of Islam on
the archipelago was the prestige and protection
that the religion brought. One example of
this in action is the king of Parameswara,
the ruler of Singapura, who had been besieged
by Majapahit under the reign of Hayam Wuruk,
and had fled north to the coast of the Malacca
Strait. There he had founded the city of Malacca,
and in order to add an heir of legitimacy
to his new rule, Parameswara seems to have
ditched his original Hindu-Buddhist
name and adopted a new Persian one,
calling himself Sultan Iskander Shah instead.
Muslim traders preferred where possible to
trade with other Muslims, who were more likely
to share their languages of Arabic or Persian,
keep the same trading and prayer hours,
and shared a common moral code. And so,
this connection helped Malacca to rapidly expand.
The new city's strategic location right on the
narrow sea corridor meant the Ming Chinese were
also very interested to bring its rulers under
their patronage and protection. When Admiral Zheng
He arrived at the port town of Malacca, he left a
stone tablet inscribed with a poem that officially
declared it under the protection of China.
The vast southwestern sea reaches unto the Middle
Kingdom, its waves cresting high as the heavens,
watering the earth the same way for countless
eons. Washed by sunlight, bathed in the moonlight,
rain-swept crags and dewy rocks in its midst
luxuriate with vegetation. And in such a place,
people live in harmony. Its righteous king,
paying his respects to imperial power,
wishes his country to be treated as one of our
imperial domains, and to follow the Chinese way.
So here, writ large on everlasting stone, we do
proclaim your loyalty. Posterity will smile upon
your deed as time passes, and your sons and
grandsons will have limitless good fortune.
In this, the Chinese were right. The port town
of Malacca would grow under Ming protection to
become the largest and most important in the whole
region. When Zheng He returned a few years later,
he would build a fort at Malacca to protect it,
and in return, the people of the city would ensure
that this crucial waterway would be controlled
by China and China alone. Wealth and trade that
would have once flowed through the ports of Java
now passed through the new trading hub of Malacca
instead. From this hub of commerce, the influence
of Islam would spread all across the islands.
For the kings of Java who ruled according to
legitimacy derived from their connection to
the Buddha and the god Shiva, each new
convert reduced their overall power.
Subsequent voyages by Zheng He's treasure fleets
would sail as far west as the Strait of Hormuz,
the city of Mecca, and Mogadishu and
Mombasa on the East African coast.
But eventually the Ming would turn
away from oceangoing exploration.
When the adventurous Yongle Emperor died, he was
replaced by more inward-looking rulers who focused
instead on the construction of the Great Wall in
the north. At one point, the Ming even outlawed
the construction of large ships, dismantling some,
and perhaps even burning some vessels in harbor.
But the decades when the vast treasure fleets
had sailed the seas left a lasting impression
on every culture that they touched, and the damage
done to the image of Javanese power was immense.
Eventually the Regreg civil war would come to an
end in Java, and the Western king Wikramawardhana,
Hayam Wuruk's son-in-law, would be victorious.
Despite his humiliating and bankrupting experience
of angering the Chinese emperor, he managed to
close in on his enemies in the Eastern Court,
and in the final bloody confrontation, the
Western forces broke through the walls of
the Eastern palace. The lord of Wirabhumi fled
in the night and escaped by boat. He was hunted
down and beheaded, and his severed head was
brought back to the capital of Majapahit.
The civil war was over and the kingdom was united
once more, but the conflict had exacted a terrible
cost. In only two years of fighting, the manpower
of Majapahit had been severely depleted. Its
treasury was on the verge of bankruptcy, and its
influence had been drastically curtailed right
at the point when powerful rivals were rising in
the north and the religion of Islam was spreading
from port to port. The center of the mandala of
power had now shifted irrevocably away from Java,
and the age of Majapahit's Empire of the
Islands would slowly but surely come to an end.
While Majapahit lost much of its overseas empire
through the beginning of the 15th century,
it still remained the preeminent
power on the island of Java,
but steadily its loss of regional status began
to erode its power even in its heartlands.
When King Wikramawardhana died in
1429, his daughter Suhita took to
the throne. She was prepared to rule in the
tradition of the great Javanese queens who
had preceded her a century earlier, Dyah
Gayatri and Tribhuwana Wijaytungadewi,
but for a number of reasons, her
rule would be beset by problems.
Chief among these was a terrible famine
that descended on Java around the year 1426,
caused by a drought. But the only source
for this is the chronicle of the Pararaton,
and by this point its reports are becoming
sparse and scarce, and contain little detail.
Next, there was a period of
food shortage that was very
long in the year of the Serpents Biting People.
Unfortunately for historians, the decline of royal
power in Java also resulted in a disruption of
the major sources that we have relied on up to
this point. Narrative texts like the Pararaton
or Book of Kings were crucial sources during the
golden age of Majapahit. But as we enter the 15th
century, the text becomes increasingly obscure and
difficult to understand. The chronicle's notes get
shorter, concerning only earthquakes and eruptions
and the deaths of kings, and they come further
and further apart. The final three pages of the
Javanese Book of Kings are just a few scraps of
seemingly unrelated information separated by
decades, with its final note coming in 1481.
Then a volcanic eruption occurred in the week of
Watu Ganung in the Saka year
Action of the Sky Sea Ekor.
Perhaps in an attempt to alleviate the effects
of the drought, Suhita had constructed a vast
reservoir named Kolam Seagaran just
to the north of the city of Majapahit.
This great pool was 800 meters by 500, and
ringed all around by banks of red brick.
Whether or not this alleviated the famine,
we will never know, but it shows the drastic
situation that the empire was facing around
this time under pressure from the environment,
from internal divisions, and increasingly from
powerful rivals. When Suhita died in 1447,
her brother Kritavijaya ruled for only four
years. He was followed by a further four kings,
all of whom ruled for only a short time, and
the relationships between them are unclear.
The kingdom erupted in civil war again in
the 1470s, and in 1478, one pretender broke
through the defences of Majapahit and killed
his brother who sat on the throne. That year
in Java would be given a name that seems to
convey the mood in the kingdom at the time;
sirna ilang kretaning bhumi , which has been
translated as Vanished and Lost is the Order
of the World. Upon his victory, this new king
had inscribed a series of stone inscriptions
that made dire warnings of the fate that would
befall any who failed to support his rule.
They will end up in the realm of Yama, the king
of the dead. They will be beaten by Yama's army
for years, innumerable. They will fall in the
cauldron of hell. They will not be reborn. So,
not only will they end up in
hell, but they will stay there,
and even if they are reborn, they will
be reborn under miserable circumstances.
It seems clear from these inscriptions
that the new king didn't feel at all
secure on the throne. Throughout
this period of political instability,
the situation for Majapahit would be made
increasingly worse by the rise of a new kind
of power on the coasts of Java. That is the
ever-increasing influence of Muslim traders.
With the powerful rival of Malacca
now exerting its influence,
Muslim merchants had become wealthier and more
influential in Java than ever before, and in
the vacuum left by royal power, these wealthy
merchants became politically powerful, too.
Now, more and more people on the coasts all
around the archipelago began to flirt with
the idea of this new religion. The Portuguese
traveller Tom Pires describes the steady advance
of Islamic power in Java at the expense of
the Hindu-Buddhists, who he calls heathens.
At the time when there were heathens along the
sea coast of Java, many merchants used to come;
Parsees, Arabs, Gujaratees, Bengalees, Malays,
and other nationalities, there being many
Moors among them. They began to trade in the
country and to grow rich. They succeeded in
way of making mosques, and mollahs came from
outside. In some places the heathen Javanese
lords themselves turned Mohammedan, and these
merchant Moors took possession of these places.
The growing influence of these coastal traders
would culminate in 1475 with the foundation of a
true Muslim kingdom on the island of Java, a power
that would call itself the Sultanate of Demak.
A port town looking north into the Java Sea,
Demak had been founded in the late 15th century,
possibly by Chinese merchants, and its
people had built a grand mosque there,
combining elements of Muslim
and Javanese architecture.
The ruler of Damak was a man named
Raden Patah, who was a vassal swearing
allegiance to Majapahit. But he soon declared
independence and claimed the title of Sultan.
As Majapahit declined, the
Sultanate of Demak would expand.
It conquered the coastal region of Tuban
by 1527, and was spreading inland as far
as Malang by 1546. For the dwindling power
of Majapahit, this was the final death nail.
Due to the slow petering out of royal
chronicles in Java, we have few details about
what exactly happened to lead to the eventual
destruction of Majapahit. But at this point,
we are able to turn to the writings of some
outside visitors to the island of Java.
Around 1513, about a hundred years
after the end of the Regreg War,
the Portuguese traveller Tom Pires visited Java.
He wrote in glowing terms about the beauty of the
landscape and the abundance of the island, but he
found the power of Majapahit already a shadow of
its former glory, as he recounts in his memoirs.
They say that the island of Java
used to rule as far as the Spice
Islands on the eastern side and
over a great part of the west,
and that it had almost all the islands
of Sumatra under its dominion and all the
islands known to the Javanese, and that it had
all this for a long time passed until about a
hundred years ago, when its power began to
diminish and it came to its present state.
Pires also alludes to some degree of political
instability in Java. According to his account,
the power of its kings had diminished
so that they were now little more than
a figurehead with the mahapatih, or prime
minister, appearing to wield greater power.
Because the Javanese have lost a great part
of their lands, the kings do not command,
nor are they taken into account, but only the
viceroy and chief captain. This man is known
and honored like the real king. All the lords
of Java obey him. Him they honor. This governor
commands in everything. He holds the king of Java
in his hands. He orders him to be given food.
The king has no voice in anything,
nor is he of any importance.
Alongside this weakening of royal
authority came the fragmentation
of the kingdom. Local lords became steadily
more powerful, with some even breaking away,
and now the Muslim sultanates
began to taste blood in the water.
The sultan of the city of Demak, Raden Patah,
knew that only one thing stood between him and
ultimate power on the island of Java; that
was the lingering remnants of Majapahit.
After only a few years, he gathered his
forces and marched on the now isolated city.
The later Muslim epic verse chronicle, the
Babad Tanah Jawi, recounts what happened
next in heroic terms as the Muslim forces
bore down on the once great capital city.
Then they agree to gather together all
Muslims with their arms. Then they set
out to Majapahit. The number of troops
was immeasurable. The city of Majapahit
was encircled. Many inhabitants submitted to
Raden Patah. Nobody dared to meet him in battle.
Marching under blue and yellow banners,
they soon arrived at the walls of Majapahit.
The later Muslim chronicles imitated elements of
previous Javanese legends, and claimed that the
last king of Majapahit was so awed at the sight
of the army approaching the city that he simply
ascended to heaven right there on the spot, and
the city was captured peacefully. At the moment
Prabu Brawijaya ascended to heaven, something
like a fireball was seen coming out of the palace
of Majapahit. It flashed like a bolt of lightning
and sounded like a terrifying thunderclap. It fell
down in Bintara. Raden Patah entered the palace.
He was astonished that he did not encounter a
single person. He wept in his heart, then left the
palace and returned to Bintara with his troops.
But we can assume that the end of Majapahit was
not as peaceful as these later chroniclers make
out. The historian Herald Van Der Linde imagines
an extreme version of the scenes that unfolded.
The soldiers met almost no resistance, and within
an hour they had taken control of the royal
palace. It was a massacre. Priests were drowned
in lotus ponds. Stable boys were stabbed as they
tried to protect the king's horses. Everything
was burned to the ground; the royal residences,
the watchtower, the pavilion with its
intricate wood carvings, the army barracks,
the elephant stalls, and the library. By noon, all
that was left of Majapahit was a heap of rubble.
However, there is little evidence of
widespread burning at the site of the city,
and no heaps of bodies or mass graves have
ever been found. But what's clear is that
at this point, human habitation at the
city of Majapahit largely came to an end.
Its people fled, and all of
its houses and workshops,
its temples and palaces, were
left to fade and crumble.
For many ordinary people, life simply
went on. But it must have been a time
of great upheaval and confusion.
The Javanese text, the Niti Sastra,
records one vision of the end of the
world that must have captured the mood
of many on the island of Java as their
world came to an end and another began.
The signs of the approaching end of this
world will be all kinds of depravity among
mankind. That is to say, the wise will
turn foolish. The holy men will become
worldly. Children will abandon their parents.
Princes will lose their empires. The little
will become great and commit depredations.
In short, everything will be in confusion.
From this moment on, the Sultanate of Demak would
be the most powerful force on the island of Java,
and the age of the Hindu-Buddhist kingdoms
on the island would come to an end.
Most remaining Hindus and Buddhists
would flee east, and took refuge on
the small island of Bali, which became
a sanctuary for their ancient culture.
Epic Hindu poems like the Bomantaka were
largely forgotten on the mainland of Java,
but in Bali they were preserved. One verse
in this poem describes the destruction
wrought by a demon king on the religious
sanctuaries of a kingdom, and we might find
it a fitting description for the final days
of Java's last Hindu-Buddhist sanctuaries.
Heaven is being destroyed and hermitages swept
away because of the swarming demons. The hermits
have left, have abandoned all and fled far away,
constantly pursued. The miserable wretches. Their
bodies are lying about in the monasteries, with
their bark clothing and woven bags flung away.
With its people gone, the city of
Majapahit would have been swiftly
reclaimed by the fast-growing forest around it.
The sophisticated drainage system that its
engineers had spent generations perfecting
the channels, the sluices, and great
reservoirs would have begun to silt up
within a decade without maintenance.
The water, with nowhere left to go,
would have pooled and spread, turning streets
into marshland, and marshland into swamp. The
red bricks that gave the ruins of Majapahit
its distinctive character were fired from the
volcanic clay of the Brantas River plain, and
in the wet heat of Java, they didn't last long.
Mosses would take hold first, then lichens and
ferns. The mortar softened and dissolved. The
strangler figs and banyan trees would move in
next, clambering over the red brick courtyards
and ceremonial gateways of the Majapahit
capital, their roots clenching the walls
in their grasp and steadily but surely pulverizing
the brick. Slower-growing teak and mahogany trees
would arrive next, shading the crumbling walls of
Majapahit beneath their canopies. As all this went
on, the great rumblings of Java's volcanoes would
have conspired to hide the ruins even further.
More than ten major eruptions of the nearby
Arjuno-Welirang and Anjasmoro volcanoes took
place in the centuries that followed, each one
burying the site of Majapahit in ever more ash,
until some of its structures lay as much as
four meters beneath the surface of the earth.
In the year 1849, a Dutch traveller called
Wolter Robert van Hoevell passed through
the site of the old city, and described
the overgrown ruins that still remained.
The entire ruins were shrouded in a dark
forest and covered with shrubs and trees.
Majestic banyan trees have rooted their roots
between the stones and pushed walls apart,
raising their crowns high above
the ruins. That is why nowadays
the Javanese also call the place
Warningin Lawang, or Banyan Gate.
The Muslim sultanates that destroyed Majapahit
would not remain the most powerful force in Java
for long. The next century would see the arrival
of other sea-born powers that would soon form
their own thalassocracies, or empires of the sea.
These were the powers of European colonialism.
In 1511, the port town of Malacca
was seized by the Portuguese,
and from there their influence would
spread all over the archipelago.
Soon other European powers would arrive,
and they would all begin to influence the
fractious political life of the island
of Java, and introduced the beginnings
of an ideology more seductive and powerful
than any religion, the force of capitalism.
The sultanates of Java would soon come under the
sway of a massive international conglomerate and
one of the first joint stock companies in the
world, the Dutch East India Company. In 1598,
a Dutch fleet of eight ships under Jacob van
Neck became the first from the Netherlands to
reach the Spice Islands of Maluku. In doing
so, they bypassed the Javanese merchants,
who had long dominated the trade. When these Dutch
ships returned to Europe in the year 1599, laden
with cloves, nutmeg, and mace, the expedition
yielded an enormous profit of around 400%. One
Dutch observer would reportedly make the following
remark upon seeing the arrival of this fleet.
As long as Holland has been Holland, there have
never arrived ships as richly laden as these.
The age of European colonialism in Southeast
Asia had now begun. Between 1602 and 1796,
the Dutch East India Company dispatched
almost a million Europeans to Asia aboard
nearly 5,000 ships, dwarfing the traffic of its
nearest rival, the British East India Company,
returning with more than 2.5 million
tons of Asian goods and enslaved people.
Throughout this colonial period, which would
ultimately see Java become a European colony,
the legacy of the ancient Javanese kingdoms
was largely ignored or intentionally obscured.
The Dutch in particular had no desire to see
the people of their new colonies rally around
the memory of any ancient kingdoms, and
mostly declined to investigate the ruins
that could be found dotted around Java.
The erasure was so extensive that in his
History of the Indian Archipelago, published
in 1820, the British writer John Crawfurd was
able to write the following. The theory of
a great monarchy and of an antecedent state
of high civilization and improvement has been
forged by the national vanity of the Javanese,
unsupported by a shadow of proof, and
contradicted by unquestionable internal evidence.
But some memory of Majapahit's glory lived on
in the minds of Java's people in their songs,
their poetry, their shadow puppet plays, and in
the manuscripts they kept in their libraries.
In 1894, in a typical expansion
of European power in East Asia,
the Dutch colonialist government intervened
on the island of Lombok to the east of Bali
to depose its king, a man named Karangasem,
who was a renowned collector of ancient texts.
After a protracted war in which
the local people resisted fiercely,
the Maharaja's palace was finally stormed by
Dutch marines on the 19th of November, 1894.
The Dutch poured into the palace, and began
a slaughter in which 2,000 were massacred.
The Maharaja was captured and died a few months
later in a colonial prison. During the fighting,
Dutch artillery set fire to the Maharaja's palace,
and while its towers burned and its roofs fell in,
the colonial troops looted the king's treasury,
and carried away more than 130 kilograms of gold,
3,000 of silver, and countless works of art.
This would become known as the Lombok treasure.
But among the looters there was also a
Dutchman named Jan Laurens Andries Brandes,
an expert in Sanskrit and Old Javanese.
This man had heard that the Maharaja
Karangasem was an avid scholar and
a collector of rare manuscripts.
As the Maharaja's palace burned, this man ran
to the ruler's library and saved what he could.
While others ran with gold heaped in their arms,
Brandes frantically gathered all of the ancient
books he could carry, and fled before the roof of
the palace could collapse. Much of the Maharaja's
collection went up in flames, and we will never
be able to read what was contained within it,
but what Brandes was able to save was packed
into a box and sent back to the colonial capital.
Inside he would later find the only existing
copy of the poem the Deshawarnana, written by
the self-effacing scribe Prapanca some 500
years earlier. In the pages of that work,
the voice of the poet could once more bring to
life the description of its great king on his
journey around the island, the lives and
concerns of the people of medieval Java,
and at least in words, the kingdom
of Majapahit could live once more.
I'd like to end this episode with an extract from
an old Javanese poem called the Siwaratrikalpa,
or the Night Ritual of Shiva, written during
the years of the decline of the Majapahit
kingdom. In this passage, a hunter named Lubdhaka
stumbles upon the ruins of an ancient temple,
and like Thomas Stamford Raffles centuries
later, would be struck by the strange
melancholy of these places where once so
many lives passed, now overgrown with jungle.
As you listen, imagine how it would feel to
watch the palaces and temples of the kingdom
of Majapahit crumbling into the earth
as its people left and its reservoirs
ran dry. Imagine wandering beneath the
shade of that teak forest and watching
the roots of banyans and silk cotton trees
slowly bind their way over the ruins, as the
layers of ash fell from the sky season after
season, and covered the works of man. Imagine
turning away and setting off into the forest
as the sun finally set on Java's golden age.
A great temple complex from ancient
times rose near a mountain stream,
and the path there was lonely. The curved trunks
of the water elephants had fallen and crumbled,
and for lack of care, its wall had almost tumbled
down. The monster heads seemed to be weeping, as
their covered faces were overgrown with creepers,
and as though sad and weary, the temple guardians
lay rolled over on the ground. The pavilions in
its courtyard were in ruins. Some of the buildings
were now only wreckage, while others were rotting
away. Their roofs were broken and had fallen in,
and beyond repair their pillars stood askew,
swaying back and forth. Heartrending was the
spectacle of the reliefs. Young maidens in stone
stood, gazing skywards, full of sorrow, because
now no wandering poets ever came to visit them.
The tower temple soared on high, and its pinnacles
served as a gathering place for weeds. The sides
were cracked, overgrown by a shady fig tree which
spread luxuriantly. All the statues were cracked
by a fearsome tangle of vines, and only the main
deity within was immovably in place, standing
firm in the center of its pedestal. Pandan trees
hung down over the rocks, with an air of sadness
quite wrapped in the mist. How they longed to be
visited by the thunder, which would bring with
it the rushing of the rain! As if in sorrow,
they let their petals droop, petals on which
someone had jotted down some words in a moment
of inspiration. For is this not an admirable
place for a wandering poet to weave his verses?
Thank you once again for listening
to the Fall of Civilizations podcast.
I'd like to thank my voice actors for this
episode; Henry Stenhouse, Michael Hajiantonis,
Alexandra Boulton, Simon Jackson, Catherine
James, Tom Marshall-Lee, Chris Harvey,
Jack Jacobs, Nick Denton, Amrit Sandhu, Paul
Casselle, Tim Stephenson, and Ameen Taher.
Readings in Old and Middle Javanese were performed
by Ferry Sanjaya and Kadha Aditya. I'd also like
to thank my historical advisor for this episode,
Dr. Alex West. Major sources used in the writing
of this episode were Majapahit by Harold Van Der
Linde, The Indianized States of Southeast Asia,
edited by Walter F. Vella and translated by Sue
Brown Cowing, When China Ruled the Seas by Louise
Levathes, and New Insights on Majapahit, edited
by Herry Yogaswara and others. A full public
list of sources will be available on Patreon,
linked in the description below. I love to hear
your thoughts and responses on social media,
so please come and tell me what you thought.
You can follow me on Bluesky at paulmmcooper.com
and on Instagram at @paulmmcooper. And if you'd
like updates about the podcast, announcements
about new episodes, as well as images, maps,
and reading suggestions, you can follow the
podcast on Bluesky at fallofcivilizations.com.
This podcast can only keep going
with the support of our generous
subscribers on Patreon. You keep me
running, you help me cover my costs,
and let me dedicate more time to researching,
writing, recording, and editing to get the
episodes out to you faster and bring as much life
and detail to them as possible. As a thank you,
all subscribers are able to listen and watch
video episodes completely ad-free. If you
enjoyed this episode, please consider heading
to patreon.com/fallofcivilizations_podcast.
For now, all the best and thanks for listening.